<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A bevvayling of the peace of Germany. Or, A discourse touching the Peace of Prague, no lesse unhappily than unjustly concluded at Prague in Bohemia, the 30. of May, 1635 Wherein the subtilties and practises of the Austrians, the weakenesse of the Saxons, the dangers of the protestants, and the justnesse of the warre, deservedly set on foot by the French and Swedes, are most evidently declared. Written in Latine by Iustus Asterius, otherwise Stella, a Germane, now one of the advocates in the Court of Parliament of Paris, and historiographer to the French King. Faithfully translated out of the Latine copie. Whereunto is prefixed a briefe summarie of the treaty of peace concluded at Prague, as aforesaid, &amp;c. Published by authority.</title>
            <title>Deploratio pacis Germanicæ. English</title>
            <author>Stella, Johannes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853006</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 976:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A bevvayling of the peace of Germany. Or, A discourse touching the Peace of Prague, no lesse unhappily than unjustly concluded at Prague in Bohemia, the 30. of May, 1635 Wherein the subtilties and practises of the Austrians, the weakenesse of the Saxons, the dangers of the protestants, and the justnesse of the warre, deservedly set on foot by the French and Swedes, are most evidently declared. Written in Latine by Iustus Asterius, otherwise Stella, a Germane, now one of the advocates in the Court of Parliament of Paris, and historiographer to the French King. Faithfully translated out of the Latine copie. Whereunto is prefixed a briefe summarie of the treaty of peace concluded at Prague, as aforesaid, &amp;c. Published by authority.</title>
                  <title>Deploratio pacis Germanicæ. English</title>
                  <author>Stella, Johannes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28, [18], 129, 110-111, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] L[egat and Eliot's Court Press] for I. H[unscott] and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the golden Lyon [by P. Stephens and C. Meredith],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Stella, Johannes.  Deploratio pacis Germanicæ.</note>
                  <note>Printers', publisher's, and booksellers' names from STC; "Eliot's Court Press pr[inted]. a-f⁴".</note>
                  <note>The first leaf contains addenda and errata.</note>
                  <note>² A1 is a cancel (printed as f4); recto catchword is "at". Variant: A1 is cancellandum; catchword is "their".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prague, Peace of, 1635 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BEWAYLING OF THE PEACE OF GERMANY. OR, A Diſcourſe touching the PEACE of PRAGVE, no leſſe unhappily than unjuſtly concluded at PRAGUE in BOHEMIA, the 30. of <hi>May,</hi> 1635. Wherein the ſubtilties and practiſes of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians,</hi> the weakeneſſe of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the dangers of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the juſtneſſe of the Warre, deſervedly ſet on foot by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> are moſt evidently declared.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Latine</hi> by <hi>Iuſtus Aſterius,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Stella,</hi> a <hi>Germane,</hi> now one of the Advocates in the Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher to the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the</hi> Latine <hi>Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is prefixed a briefe Summarie of the Treaty of Peace concluded at <hi>Prague,</hi> as aforeſaid, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREM. 6. v. 14. and 8. v. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people ſlightly, ſaying, Peace, peace, when there is no peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>I H.</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the golden Lyon. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18364:2"/>
            <head>THE CHIEFE HEADS AND CONCLVSIONS OF THE TREATIE OF Peace held at <hi>Prague,</hi> are contained in the three Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts enſuing.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>A</hi> Summarie Extract out of the Treatie of Peace made and concluded betwixt the Emperour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> at <hi>Prague,</hi> the <hi>30.</hi> day of May, <hi>1635.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18364:3"/>
               <item>II. An Extract of the Agreement made betwixt the Emperour and the ſaid Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ioyning of their Armes together.</item>
               <item>III. An Extract tranſlated word for word out of the ſaid Treatie, touching the <hi>Palatinate</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18364:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> An Abridgement of the Treatie of the Peace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Revenues of th Church, which were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> before the Treatie of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> ſhall remaine entirely in the ſame ſtate they were ſetled in by the ſaid Treatie of <hi>Paſſaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church-Revenues poſſeſſed by them ſince the ſaid Treatie, ſhall be left unto them for the ſpace of fortie yeeres, upon the conditions more ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and expreſſed in this agreement, as well for the Spirituall, as for the Temporall.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18364:4"/>
               <p>And ten yeeres before the expiration of the ſaid Terme, the beſt endeavour ſhall be uſed to make a finall accord, for ſo much as concerneth the ſaid Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, and that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth of them: But if that cannot be done, it ſhall then be in the power of the Emperour to make a deciſion of the difference: And in the meane time, there ſhall no more Church-Poſſeſſions be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the <hi>Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Magdebourg</hi> ſhall remaine to Duke <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſonne to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> during his life, upon ſuch conditions as are expreſſed in this agreement as well for the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as for the Spirituall.</p>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> ſhall have the Seignories and Bayliwickes of <hi>Querfurt, Iuterbock, Dama,</hi> and <hi>Borck;</hi> which Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he ſhall hold in Fee of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick of <hi>Magdebourg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Marquis <hi>Chriſtian William,</hi> ſhall have 12000 Rix-Dollars given him by the yeere out of the Revenues of the ſaid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18364:4"/> Archbiſhoprick, during his life, for his entertainment.</p>
               <p>The Archduke <hi>Leopold William,</hi> the Emperours ſonne, ſhall have, amongſt other things, the Biſhoprick of <hi>Halber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Nobilitie and Gentrie of the Empire ſhall be left to their free exerciſe of the Confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurgh;</hi> as ſhall alſo thoſe Imperiall Cities, which ſhall conforme themſelves to this Treatie: But thoſe which before the concluſion of the ſaid Treatie, ſhall have accorded alreadie in any other manner with the Emperour, ſhall hold themſelves to that accord.</p>
               <p>The Citie of <hi>Donawerth</hi> ſhall remaine in the hands of the Duke of <hi>Baviere,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he be re-emburſed his charges.</p>
               <p>The free exerciſe of the Confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurgh</hi> ſhall no more be tolerated for the time to come in the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> nor in the other Hereditarie Countries of the Emperour.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Sileſia,</hi> the Emperour hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18364:5"/> his reſolution by it ſelfe, and hath made a particular accord with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> for <hi>Luſatia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The propoſitions made by the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> That the Imperiall Chamber may from henceforth be divided, and compoſed of perſons of both Religions, equall in number; are put off unto the firſt generall Aſſembly, which ſhall be holden hereafter: In the meane time, the order ſhal be obſerved which is practiſed in the ſaid Imperiall Chamber. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there hath been no Viſitation ſince the yeere 1600, there ſhall be one as ſoone as poſſibly may be extraordinarily.</p>
               <p>The inſtruction of the Aſſeſſors and Preſidents of the Court <hi>Aulike,</hi> or of the <hi>Councell</hi> following the Emperors perſon, ſhall be ſubmitted to the advice of all the Electors but the ſaid Aſſeſſors ſhall not be of both Religions, in equall number.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Electors, Princes, and States, ſhall be permitted to have their Agents and Sollicitors in the ſaid <hi>Aulike</hi> Court.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18364:5"/>
               <p>The <hi>Palatine Electorate,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries belonging to it, ſhall remaine unto the Duke of <hi>Baviere,</hi> and to the Line of Duke <hi>William</hi> his father, according as the Emperour hath ordered: And that which his Imperiall Majeſtie hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed touching the eſtates of ſome of the <hi>Palatines</hi> ſervants, ſhall remaine entire as it is.</p>
               <p>The Widow of the Elector <hi>Frederick</hi> the fourth, Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> ſhall enjoy her Iointure, for ſo much as ſhe can make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be due unto her.</p>
               <p>An entertainment of a Prince ſhall be given to the children of <hi>Frederick</hi> the proſcribed, if they doe in due manner humble themſelves towards the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: But this not to be done as a thing due, but of his Imperiall grace.</p>
               <p>The heires of the Count <hi>Tilly</hi> deceaſed ſhall have 400000 Rix-Dollars out of the Revenues of the Duchy of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> payable in eight yeres, with intereſt after five in the hundred, untill it be fully payd: and in the meane time, they ſhall keepe that which is morgaged unto them.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18364:6"/>
               <p>If the Dukes of <hi>Meckelburgh</hi> doe accept theſe Articles of Pacification, they ſhall be received into the <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> according as is contained in the particular Order made concerning that matter.</p>
               <p>The Electors, Princes, and States of the Confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurgh</hi> ſhall reſtore to the Emperour, and to the <hi>Catholike</hi> Electors, Princes, &amp; States, his aſſiſtants, as alſo unto the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> their Countreyes, Lands, Seignories, Cities, Townes, Caſtles, and all that belongs unto them. Yet nevertheleſſe, they ſhall not be tyed to make reſtitution of the Revenues received, nor of their charges expended in the Warre; but they ſhall not carry away the Ordnance, nor their moveable goods, out of the places which they ſhall give up.</p>
               <p>Ayde and aſſiſtance ſhall be given, by a conjunction of Armes and Forces, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that which the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the States of the Empire, which will not conforme themſelves to this preſent Treatie, doe poſſeſſe within the Empire.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18364:6"/>
               <p>The Emperour and his aſſiſtants ſhall reſtore the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and thoſe of his party, their ſubjects, vaſſalls, men, and ſervants, to the poſſeſſion of their eſtates, if they accept of this Treatie; excepting thoſe, whom the Emperour hath expreſſely excluded from it: And the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and thoſe of his party, ſhall doe the ſame reciprocally to the Emperour and his aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p>The places poſſeſſed by the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> ſince the yeere 1625, (amongſt which, <hi>Wolfenbottle</hi> and <hi>Newburgh</hi> are intended to be of the number) ſhall be reſtored to their proprietarie Lords, without reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them the Revenues of them, and without carrying away the Ordnance.</p>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> ſhall reſtore within ten dayes, that he yet holdeth in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and ſhall give ayde towards the diſlodging of the Souldiers of the other party, which ſhall be found with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that Kingdome.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of his party, ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18364:7"/> ayde the Emperour and his aſſiſtants, for the recoverie of their Poſſeſſions, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to this Treatie: And the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, with his aſſiſtants, ſhall ayde the ſaid Elector and his, in the recoverie of that which belongeth unto them.</p>
               <p>If the Elector of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> who is not excluded from the <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> will accept of this Peace, he ſhall be inveſted in the Duchie of <hi>Pomeranie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All labour and endeavour ſhall be joyntly uſed, to deliver <hi>Pomeranie,</hi> the upper and nether Circle of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the whole Empire in generall, from ſtrange Souldiers.</p>
               <p>When this ſhall be done, and the Houſe of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> ſhall have accepted this Treatie, rid away his Souldiers, and ſhall have conformed it ſelfe, then <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenbottle</hi> and other places ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto him.</p>
               <p>When the Emperour, the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto them, in the upper and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18364:7"/> nether Circle of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and in the Circles of <hi>Suaube, Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> ſo as they may fully and peaceably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it; the ſaid <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhall alſo fully enjoy and have the benefit of this Peace.</p>
               <p>If the Emperour doth ſtill entertaine Garriſons in ſome places within the ſaid Circles; that ſhall not prejudice the ſaid <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> nor ſhall hinder them from returning thither, and enjoying their Right.</p>
               <p>And as it is provided, that the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> ſhall be reſtored to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all his Countries, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances; ſo it ſhall not be ſuffered, that from henceforth any thing more whatſoever be taken from him.</p>
               <p>The Emperour reſerveth unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Fort of <hi>Philipsbourg,</hi> to diſpoſe of it hereafter, as ſhall ſeeme good unto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The Priſoners, and their Principalls, to whom they belong, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelves to this Treatie, ſhall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18364:8"/> be releaſed within one moneth after the publication of the Peace: Yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, thoſe who have alreadie promiſed their ranſome, ſhall pay it, with the charges which they have expended.</p>
               <p>There ſhall be a generall <hi>Amneſtia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Emperour, the <hi>Catholike</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Princes, and States, his aſſiſtants, and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and thoſe which have beene of his partie in this Warre; in ſuch manner and ſort, that all which hath beene done and committed hoſtilely, ſince the yeere 1630, untill this time, ſhall be aboliſhed and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, if they doe accept of this Peace within ten dayes: Which <hi>Amneſtia</hi> ſhall be extended alſo unto their Heires, Lands, Countries, People, and Subjects, their Officers of Warre, Souldiers, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, Servants, and Miniſters.</p>
               <p>The Emperour hath excluded out of this <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> the Affaires and Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and of the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> For ſince that his Imperiall Majeſtie, for the quieting of them, hath been conſtrained
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18364:8"/> to put himſelfe to very great charges; he will ſeeke for reparation of his Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages upon them, who have beene the cauſers of them, and upon their Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p>He doth alſo exclude from this <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestia,</hi> all the perſons and eſtates, which are ſpecified in a Schedule, which hath been exhibited of them unto the Elector of <hi>Saxonie:</hi> Which excluſion and excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid perſons and their eſtates, expreſſed in the ſaid Schedule, ſhall be held as firme and availeable, to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and put in execution, as if the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of them were here inſerted word for word.</p>
               <p>The States, which have already made their accommodation with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſhall hold themſelves to their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and ſhall have no power to make any pretence to any further matter, by vertue of this.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which have hitherto remained Neuters, and will accept of this Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſhall enjoy the ſaid <hi>Amneſtia.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18364:9"/>
               <p>The forraine Potentates, which have intereſſed themſelves in this Warre, ſince the yeere 1630, ſhall be alſo comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the ſaid <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> if they will conforme themſelves to this Treatie.</p>
               <p>The Emperour will take it to his charge, to publiſh, notifie, and alſo to advance, promote, and confirme by his Edicts and Commandements, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Treatie, and that which depends of it: He will exhort and ſtirre up every one to joyne his Armes to thoſe of his Imperiall Majeſtie, and to ſignifie in what ſtate, condition, and poſture hee findes himſelfe, and what his Forces are: Which ſignification, or advertiſement, every man ſhall give, either to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himſelfe, or (if he cannot doe that, by reaſon of the dangerouſneſſe of the Wayes) to the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> or to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> or to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Mentz, Collen, Bavaria,</hi> or to the generall and principall Officers.</p>
               <p>The end or ayme of this Pacification, is, to reſtore the Empire to her ancient
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18364:9"/> tranquillitie and libertie: And to this purpoſe, the Emperour ſhall continue armed; and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the other Electors, Princes, and States, ſhall joyne their troupes to thoſe of his Imperiall Majeſtie: And of all their Armies, ſhall be made one principall one, which ſhall be called, <hi>The Armie of his Imperiall Majeſtie, and of the ſacred Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the fourth part of the ſaid Armie, in a Body by it ſelfe; and the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> ſhall command the other three parts, in another Body, or in divers, as it ſhall be found expedient.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Armie ſhall be employed againſt all thoſe that ſhall oppoſe this Treatie of Pacification, or that ſhall not be willing to give uſe that they poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>All the Bodies of their Armies, and all their Generalls and Officers, ſhall ſweare allegeance to the Emperour.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding, the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18364:10"/> they ſhall command in perſon, ſhall not be ſummoned to take their corporall Oath; but it ſhall ſuffice, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage their Word, Honour, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Royall and Electorall, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively.</p>
               <p>The Emperour will cauſe the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Capitulations (Articles briefe) to be framed, as neere as may be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Lawes and Statutes of the Empire.</p>
               <p>The whole Body of the Empire ſhall contribute to the entertainment of the ſaid Imperiall Armie; and the States ſhall make no difficultie to furniſh and pay, preſently after the publication, 120 moneths of the contribution of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, called <hi>Romertzug.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The charges and expences of quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Armie, ſhall be defalked out of the ſaid contribution, in ſuch ſort, that thoſe who have beene at the charge of quartering and lodging the Souldiers, ſhall abate out of their taxation ſo much as they have expended that way.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18364:10"/>
               <p>The Emperour will call an Imperiall Dyet as ſoone as poſſibly can be, as well for the ſetling and advancing of the ſaid contribution of the Empire, as for the other publike affaires of the Empire.</p>
               <p>When the Peace ſhall be fully re-eſtabliſhed, then all lodging of Souldiers and all ſorts of arming ſhall ceaſe.</p>
               <p>No forraine Forces ſhall be ſuffered to enter into the Empire, for any cauſe whatſoever, nor for the difference concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By vertue of this Pacification and Agreement, all other Vnions, Leagues, and Alliances within the Empire, ſhall be diſannulled and made void; except the Agreements and Contracts of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, made betwixt Noble Houſes.</p>
               <p>The Emperour will hold good intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with his neighbour Kingdomes, which doe no oppreſſion upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
               <p>His Imperiall Majeſtie will reigne and governe the Empire with mildneſſe and clemencie.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18364:11"/>
               <p>On the other ſide, the Electors, Princes, and States, will render him all the reſpect and obedience they owe him.</p>
               <p>Alſo good amitie ſhall be maintained betwixt the parties.</p>
               <p>For the advancement of the Peace, and of Iuſtice, the Electors, Princes, and States ſhall hold good correſpondence with the Emperour.</p>
               <p>The Conſtitutions of execution, and that which is ordained by this Treatie, ſhall be obſerved againſt thoſe that ſhall keepe themſelves armed, in prejudice of this Pacification.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever ſhall be done and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the tenor of this Treatie, ſhall be held void <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditie.</p>
               <p>The Emperour doth promiſe, by his Imperiall Dignitie, to obſerve what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is concluded by this Treatie; and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> doth the ſame.</p>
               <p>If then the Electors, Princes, and States of the Empire, or the greater part
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18364:11"/> of them, doe accept this Pacification and Agreement; it ſhall be held for a common reſolution, and fundamentall Law of the Empire: in conformitie whereunto, the Iudges of Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhall give ſentence againſt thoſe that ſhall infringe the ſame.</p>
               <p>The Emperour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> have called to minde, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of ſo high importance, which concerneth the whole Body of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ought not to have beene made, but in a Dyet of the Empire, or in an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Deputation: But for as much as the urgent neceſsitie hereof, could not give leave to ſtay for the occaſion of ſuch an Aſſembly; it is by way of precaution declared, that this reſolution ſhall not prejudice the right and libertie of the Empire, for the time to come.</p>
               <p>Three ſeverall Exemplifications in Parchment have beene made and ſigned of this preſent Treatie, and all of one and the ſame tenor: whereof, one was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Emperour; the other, to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18364:12"/> Elector of <hi>Mentz,</hi> as Arch-Chancellor of the Empire, to regiſter it amongſt the publike Acts and Records of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and the third, to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Given at</hi> Prague, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of May,</hi> 1635.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> An Extract out of the particular Accord made betwixt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> touching the ioyning together of their Armes.</head>
               <p>ALL the Forces ſhall be reduced into one <hi>Armade,</hi> which ſhall be called, <hi>The</hi> Armade <hi>of his Imperiall Majeſtie, and of the ſacred Empire;</hi> and a good part of it ſhall be left to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> to be commanded. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ſhall be this: If the Armie doe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18364:12"/> amount unto 80000 men, the Emperour ſhall have 60000 of them; which he ſhall cauſe to be commanded by the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> his Sonne: and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> ſhall have 20000 to command; and if the ſaid Elector have foure or five thouſand over and above that number, he ſhall be ſuffered to have them. All theſe Souldiers ſhall be entertained with the contributions of the Empire; and the Receivers generall ſhall be tyed to furniſh to every Generall his rate, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of the Body of the Armie which he ſhall command. If the Emperour happen to depart this life, the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> his Sonne, and he whom it ſhall pleaſe him to ordaine, ſhall continue the command of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of his Armie. And if the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> happen to dye, his Sonne, who is to be his Succeſſour in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorate, ſhall ſucceed his Father alſo in his place of Generall. If the ſaid Elector, or his Sonne, doe deſire to be diſcharged of the Bodie of his Armie,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18364:13"/> he ſhall be ſo; and the Emperour will entruſt the Command of Generall of that Body of the Army, to ſome other of the Confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurgh;</hi> ſuch as the ſaid Elector, and the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> ſhall adviſe him unto. When any execution ſhall be commanded, and committed to one of the ſaid Bodies of Armies, it ſhall be obedient, to undertake it; without any diſturbance to be given unto them, in the ſaid execution, by the other Bodies of Armies: and if that Body be not found ſufficient for the action, the others ſhall readily and willingly aſſiſt it: To the effecting whereof, the Generalls and Directors ſhall hold a carefull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence together, and ſhall direct all their actions to one and the ſame end. They ſhall as ſoone as poſſibly may be, and at the furtheſt, within foure or ſixe weekes after the publication hereof, take their Oath of Allegeance unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and the Empire, as is mentioned in the Treatie of Pacification. In the places where <hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18364:13"/> dwell, the quarters ſhall be equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, without any diſtinction of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If any Warre doe happen to be made in the Circles of high and low <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> as being neighbour unto it, have a deſire to doe execution rather then another, or to quarter himſelfe there, the Emperour will grant him leave to doe it, before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In caſe, that the Elector of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> or his Sonne, ſhould not be in perſon in the Campe, and that neceſſitie did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that they ſhould joyne the Bodies of the Armies together; then the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> ſhall have the direction of the Body of the Armie of the ſaid E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector: and the levyes of Souldiers, and their quartering, ſhall be proportioned according to the Bodies of the Armies. The Receivers generall of the Empire ſhall be bound by Oath, to pay and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the contribution-Mony to each Body of the Armies proportionably, that is to ſay, to the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> for 60000, and to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> for 20000 men.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18364:14"/> When it ſhall pleaſe God to re-eſtabliſh the Peace, and that the Troupes ſhall come to be disbanded, this proportion ſhall be obſerved; That as the Elector ſhall disband 2000 men, the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> ſhall disband 6000. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not found to be comprehended nor expreſſed in this Schedule or Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Agreement, is to be ſought for in the Contents of the Treatie of Peace at large, which ought to be invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably obſerved.</p>
               <p>Of this Schedule there have beene made two Exemplifications in Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of one and the ſame tenor: The one, for the Emperour; the other, for the Elector of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Given at</hi> Prague, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of May,</hi> 1635.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18364:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> An Extract out of the ſaid Treatie of Peace, for ſo much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TOuching the buſineſſe of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> as being that for which in theſe yeeres laſt paſt many horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commotions, Troubles, and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions have beene rayſed; His Electorall Highneſſe of <hi>Saxonie</hi> did very ſtiffely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon it, to have it fully ſetled and accommodated, as well in point of the Electorall Dignitie, as for that which concerneth his Countreyes: But for as much as it is notoriouſly knowne, (and the moſt laudable College of Electors judged it to be ſo at <hi>Mulbauſen,</hi> in the yeere 1627) that the proſcribed <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Frederick,</hi> hath beene the Author
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18364:15"/> and Promoter of all the Miſchiefes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> an Hereditarie King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Imperiall Majeſtie, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after in the Empire; and that his Imperiall Majeſtie, together with his moſt honourable Houſe, findes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be in debt for this occaſion many Millions, and to have ſuſtained divers other great Damages; and namely, that he hath beene conſtrained to leave ſome part of his Hereditarie Countreyes in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reare, to furniſh the expences of the Warre: His Majeſtie would by no meanes depart from his reſolution, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Electorall Highneſſe of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> did ſeriouſly beſtow his labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And therefore that remained firme and ſetled, which his Imperiall Majeſtie had ordained and determined, touching the ſaid Electorall Dignitie, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes; as well on the behalfe of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Highneſſe of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Line of the late Duke <hi>William</hi> his Father, as otherwiſe; and alſo, touching the eſtates of ſome of the <hi>Palatines</hi> Servants.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18364:15"/> Yet nevertheleſſe, the Widow of the late Elector, <hi>Frederick</hi> the fourth, Count <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſhall have her Iointure allowed her, ſo farre forth as ſhe can make appeare what belongeth to her. Alſo the entertainment of a Prince ſhall be ordered to be allowed to the Children of the proſcribed <hi>Palatine,</hi> if they will duely humble themſelves towards his Imperiall Majeſtie. And all this to be done of his Imperiall grace, not as any thing of due.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Below.</head>
                  <p>HIS Imperiall Majeſtie doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely exclude and cut off from this <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> the Affaires and Differences of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate.</hi> And becauſe, for the appeaſing and quieting of them, his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie hath brought himſelfe and his Houſe into great and heavie Expences;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18364:16"/> and that he hath (as hath beene formerly ſaid) beene conſtrained to leave in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reare ſome part of his Hereditarie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, of the profits whereof he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet fruſtrate, and unſatisfied; his Majeſtie hath reſerved unto himſelfe the ſeeking of reſtitution of the Charges ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended by him, and the reparation of the Damages ſuſtained by him, from them who have beene the cauſers thereof, and from their aſſiſtants and promoters; and eſpecially from as many of them as can be found, that have not yet by other Accords accommodated and reconciled themſelves to his ſaid Imperiall Majeſtie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:16"/>
            <head>The Tranſlation of the Authors Epiſtle Dedicatorie to the French King. TO LOVYS XIII. THE MOST CHRISTIAN KING OF FRANCE AND NAVARRE, <hi>I. A. D.</hi> wiſheth Victorie, and eternall felicitie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie a defence of the common Quarrell and Libertie, which the whole World expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and waiteth for, from the happie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of your deſignes: Her Cauſe can more juſtly be conſecrated to
<pb facs="tcp:18364:17"/> none, becauſe it can more powerfully be defended by none. This Controverſie, touching a matter of ſingular excellencie, is publike; and therefore ought not to be agitated, but before them, upon whom the publike ſafetie relyeth. The ſecuritie of the Chriſtian World is invaded; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſsiſtance is to be craved from Him alone, who onely can when he will, and will when he can, reſtore peace and tranquillitie to the World. The ambition of the Enemies, is inſatiable: whileſt it is preparing a Warre for <hi>Europe,</hi> it publiſhed a counterfeit Peace to the <hi>Germans.</hi> To the end, that it may openly deceive, it doth ſecretly make an agreement; that it may more ſafely beguile men unarmed, it doth in name onely baniſh Warre out of the Empire: This fraudulent agreement hath beene rejected by the valour of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> repelled by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the <hi>French,</hi> and deſpiſed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> For this cauſe, they are proſcribed as Enemies of the common peace, and diſturbers of the publike quiet; and although they doe with force of Armes ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the common Concord, yet being left deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and innocent, they beare the blame of the
<pb facs="tcp:18364:17"/> continued Warre. By this Worke, we anſwere that Calumnie, and turning backe the points of the Darts upon our Adverſaries, we ſhew, that they onely are the Confederate Enemies of Peace, who carrying ordinarily in their mouthes the name of Quiet, doe meditate in their hearts perpetuall Warres and Diſcords; and masking their Tyrannie with the name of Libertie, their Invaſion with Pietie, and their Conſpiracies with publike Securitie, with a counterfeit ſhew and ſpecious colour, doe attribute moſt honeſt names unto moſt diſ-honeſt actions, and moſt diſ-honeſt actions unto moſt honeſt names. As if your Majestie, and yours, did of your owne accord take Armes againſt them, and not by compulſion repell Armes, voluntarily taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you and your Confederates; or, as if they did ever offer any Peace unto you, but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt one, or you ever refuſed any juſt one; or, as if they can hope for any firme tranquillitie, as long as they retaine to themſelves thoſe eſtates of other mens, which they have, and lay claime to thoſe they have not. But men, who have no colour of title to poſſeſſe things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtrangers, have need to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:18364:18"/> to fallacies of words, thereby to deceive thoſe that will beleeve them, as well by words as by deeds. <hi>You, SIR,</hi> who have Iuſtice for your Companion in all your doings, need no caſes, or out-ſides of words; but you doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſse in words the ſinceritie which you practiſe in your life. For you keeping a Watch over the publike tranquillitie, and not over your owne private benefit, doe ſo defend that which is your owne, that you covet not that which is another mans; you doe ſo protect your friends, that you doe not oppreſſe them as your enemies; and though your ſelfe doe injurie to none, yet you revenge the injurie done to your Confederates; and doe advance the bounds of your Empire rather by the glory of your brave actions, then by the extending of your Territories. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it falleth out, that as there can be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of peoples, or parallell of ſtrength be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your ſubjects and friends, and your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo there is alſo a vaſt diſsimilitude of cauſes. They profeſsing a horrible ambition of ruling over all, out of the private and greedie deſire of Soveraigntie, doe pick a quarrell againſt the Church, and doe raiſe the Armes of the Empire
<pb facs="tcp:18364:18"/> unprovoked, in a moſt violent manner, againſt thoſe that would oppoſe them; they doe compell the people, by enticing and drawing them on with ſpecious ſhewes and names of things, to ſerve their ambition; and endevour to bring all <hi>Germanie</hi> under their yoke meerly through neceſsitie of deſpaire; having beene for many yeeres paſt pittifully oppreſſed with a moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Warre, and exhauſted of all her ſtrength and wealth. Your Majestie being content with the Territories of your fore-fathers, and your owne triumphs, doth never take Armes, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your will; never lay them downe, but willingly; and having uſed them onely for the defence of your ſubjects, your friends, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right, doth maintaine the libertie of all, the ſecuritie of every one, and the ſafetie of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> with no leſſe clairitie then you go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ne them with equitie. Whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that whereas the captivitie of the Empire ſeemeth to be greedily gaped after by them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie of libertie is endevoured and effected by you; the World is troubled by them, pacified by you, and <hi>Germanie,</hi> oppreſſed by them, is relieved and reſtored by you. And let all things
<pb facs="tcp:18364:19"/> be ſo ſubject to the Lawes of Heaven, that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Vertue, and Felicitie fighting on your ſide, and Trecherie, Cowardiſe, and Calamitie taking part with your Enemies, Providence may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that ſhe oweth Victorie to the one, and Vengeance to the other. Therefore, <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> be pleaſed to entertaine this Opening and Pleading of the Publike Cauſe, and to take knowledge of the Innocencie of this continued Warre, preſented to you in writing, as you doe defend and countenance it in action. Let your Majeſties protection be open to the defence of Libertie, who even from your tender age have ever beene a Sanctuarie to the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, a Refuge to your Confederates, a ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the afflicted, and a moſt certaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to all people. Your friends relying upon this, will not feare any Warre from their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and will hope for a Peace from you, that ſhall uphold Law and Iuſtice: Which Peace, when you ſhall have redeemed the Right of common Libertie, you will reſolve upon; having reſolved, you will give it; and having given it, you will preſerve it for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:19"/>
            <head>A Breviate or ſhort View of the whole WORKE.</head>
            <p>The Treatie of <hi>Prague,</hi> concluded by the Emperour and Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> againſt the <hi>Protestants, Swedes,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> is proved to be of no validitie, void, and unjuſt, by five ſeverall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or generall Nullities.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Nullitie, on the Emperours part. <hi>Pag. 1.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. BEcauſe a Treatie or determination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Lands, exceedeth the power of the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 6</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe it is founded upon the Tranſaction of <hi>Paſsaw,</hi> which is of no moment with the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians. p.</hi> 8</item>
                  <item>3. The Emperours themſelves doe confeſſe, that it belongeth not to their power, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing in matter of Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 15</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18364:20"/>
                  <item>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> by any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>p.</hi> 17</item>
                  <item>5. Becauſe the Treatie of <hi>Prague</hi> it ſelfe is very ignominious to the Emperour and to the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes. p.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Nullitie, on the part of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie. Pag. 25.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe, though he account himſelfe the chiefe of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> yet by this divorce and ſeparation from them, he utterly ruineth both his owne ſtrength, and the ſtrength of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes. <hi>p.</hi> 26</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe the treating of a common Peace, exceedeth the power of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie. p.</hi> 28</item>
                  <item>3. Becauſe this Tranſaction of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> is hurtfull and deceitfull to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants. p.</hi> 31</item>
                  <item>4. It ſpringeth from a fountaine of foule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and horrible trecherie. <hi>p.</hi> 35</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third Nullitie, on the part of the Protestants. <hi>Pag. 43.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> being inſtigated by the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> made Warre againſt the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 43</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe they are enforced to conſent, not to a Peace, but to a new Warre. <hi>p.</hi> 48</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18364:20"/>
                  <item>3. The Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is unjuſtly made Hereditarie to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria. p.</hi> 55</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Sileſia</hi> being innocent, is ſtripped of her rights. <hi>p.</hi> 64</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Luſatia</hi> is unjuſtly diſmembred from the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia. p.</hi> 66</item>
                  <item>6. The Electorall dignitie of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> is unjuſtly tranſlated to the <hi>Bavarian. p.</hi> 73</item>
                  <item>7. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> anciently had no right to the Electorate. <hi>p.</hi> 84</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>The fourth Nullitie, on the part of the <hi>Swedes. Pag. 95.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the <hi>Swedes</hi> making Warre in their owne name, ought alſo to make the accord in their owne right. <hi>p.</hi> 98</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe the Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> in his owne private name oweth revenging imprecations to the <hi>Swedes. p.</hi> 101</item>
                  <item>3. Becauſe the <hi>Swedes</hi> cannot baſely abandon their Leagues, nor their Troupes: Nor dare they make any agreement with the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> under the faithleſſe undertaking of the <hi>Saxon. p.</hi> 104</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>The fifth Nullitie, on the part of the <hi>French. Pag. 110.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the <hi>moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> by right of protection, preſerved the <hi>Catholike</hi> Faith in the Empire. <hi>p.</hi> 111</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18364:21"/>
                  <item>2. The protection of the Princes and States of the Empire, cannot be charged to be the <hi>French</hi> Kings fault. <hi>p.</hi> 116</item>
                  <item>3. The moſt illuſtrious Elector of <hi>Trevers</hi> (or <hi>Trier</hi>) did juſtly and ſeaſonably obtaine the protection of the <hi>French. p.</hi> 120</item>
                  <item>4. Becauſe the Emperour endeavoureth to make the private quarrels of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the <hi>French,</hi> common to the whole Empire. <hi>p.</hi> 124</item>
                  <item>5. Becauſe the cauſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> doth nothing at all belong to the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 127</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore the concluſion is, that this Triumvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſpiracie ought to be rejected, and a true, honeſt, and univerſall Peace to be fought for, and defended with the common Armes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Vpon the birth or deliverie of the Tranſaction of <hi>Prague.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>VNgodly <hi>Prague,</hi> which to the World</l>
               <l>a bloudie Warre hath brought,</l>
               <l>From her falſe Wombe, how ever could</l>
               <l>a faithfull Peace be ſought?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Or,</head>
               <l>Vngodly <hi>Prague</hi> hath to the World</l>
               <l>a bloudie Warre projected,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Prague</hi> a Plague, and no firme Peace</l>
               <l>could ever be expected.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18364:21"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost venerable is the name of Peace; the plentie it brings, is comfortable; and the happineſſe of it, moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; the poſſeſſion of it, is ever bleſsed; and the granting of it, at all times to be laboured for. Certainely, I cannot imagine any mortall man to be ſo void of humanitie, that he would envie a Reſt ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to the Empire, ſo beneficiall to the Countrey; as being that, without which neither private families, nor publike Lawes, nor the right of common ſocietie can ſubſist. I cannot ſuppoſe any man to be ſo barbarous and ſavage, that, all other circumſtances and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being alike, will preferre a Souldiers Coat before a Gowne, Warre before Peace; when as in this change and viciſſitude of affaires, by buſineſſe and labour, is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten eaſe; by troubles, reſt; and by Armes, love and concord. But where libertie and the ſafetie of the Common-wealth is pretended, and ſervitude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction intended; where a moſt unjuſt and trecherous Combination, is veiled with the glorious name of a Peace; where, under a pretext of Reſt, the reſtleſſe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier doth ranſack and ſpoile mens habitations; and laſtly, where a deceitfull Condition of Mercie is a Bait
<pb facs="tcp:18364:22"/> to draw on inſulting Power: every wiſe man will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre even a doubtfull Warre, before a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peace; uncertaine ſafetie, before a certaine deſtruction; and an unſworne condition of ſlaverie, before a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Soveraigntie. I confeſse, that nothing can happen to miſerable <hi>Germanie,</hi> either more certaine, for her ſafetie, more noble, for her glory; or more to be wiſhed, for the recoverie of her former felicitie; then, if by conſent of the Princes, and Pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie of the Nobles, it may be reſtored to her ancient concord, and now almoſt quite forgotten tranquillitie: And that no leſse Honour ſhould be gained to that Emperour, who with the ſweet Bond of Peace ſhould reduce to unitie his Countrey, exhauſted with ſlaughters and butcherie; his peoples, enraged and made furious with the injuries of former times, and like Savages exerciſing their Cruelties upon their owne Bowels; then there was Divinitie aſcribed to him, who firſt joyned together in one Body ſo many Nations, no leſse different in manners and diſpoſition, then in ſituation of Climates; and by communion of Lawes and Cuſtomes, made them the moſt flouriſhing Common-wealth of <hi>Europe.</hi> But lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proclaimes, that by that agreement or tranſaction of <hi>Prague,</hi> hatreds were not mitigated, but inflamed; Armes not layd downe, but doubled; proſcription and confiſcations not diminiſhed, but extended beyond all Law and right. For after that, in the very frontiſpice of the buſineſse, forraine Princes were at the firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; in the progreſſe thereof, moſt of the Caſtles, Cities, and Countreyes of <hi>Germanie,</hi> were divided amongst the great men; the reſt, that were weaker in
<pb facs="tcp:18364:22"/> ſtrength, not in cauſe, being proſcribed, were ſtripped out of their Hereditarie Iuriſdictions; the ſpoiles of the Provinces, the bootie and pillage of the baniſhed, and the goods of the ſlaughtered, were diſtributed to ſuch as did applaud the action. Next after that, for the confirming and maintaining of theſe Vſurpations, and Armie of <hi>do</hi> Regiments was impoſed upon <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie;</hi> and, as if the Lawes and Courts of Iustice did abhorre this Pacification, the Buſineſſes of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Chamber and holy Conſiſtorie were left altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undecided. No comfort or eaſe at all appeared from this Peace, nor the laſt fruit of a publike Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie; but in ſtead thereof, an unappeaſable Warre is denounced againſt all, that had or ſhould dare to complaine of the injuries offered, or ſo much as to whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the unjuſtneſse of this Conſpiracie. Nothing was here done, that was fit to be done in a lawfull Peace: the former Contributions of the States, the pilling and ſpoiling of the Countreyes, the burthens and oppreſſions of the ſubjects were not taken away, nor ſo much as mitigated, but exceſſively encreaſed, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by publike Edict; and of Souldiers payes, that were extraordinarie, and without order, were made ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie taxations. Barbarous Nations were not carried away, nor caſt out of the Empire, but made to overflow it like a deluge, and let in by multitudes at the gates, ſet wide open. And I need not ſtick to ſay, that Cities were emptied of their Citizens, the very Deſerts filled with fugitives, the goods of men and Cities, of a knowne and well-approved innocencie, confiſcated, their perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded, and their lives rated at high ſummes of money.
<pb facs="tcp:18364:23"/> So that it is more cleare then the Noone-day, that in this foreſaid tranſaction, it was not ſo much laboured to relieve the ſinking fortunes of the Countrey, as it was by all meanes endevoured, that the remaining States of the Empire ſhould be deluded with the name of a Peace; that the remaining ſtrength of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould ſuccour then afflicted condition of the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> that the common Armes ſhould with their whole power be turned againſt Rebels (as they call them) and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: and ſo in ſtead of concord, to have diſcord; in ſtead of truth, trecherie; and in ſtead of a iuſt Warre, a most wicked and detestable one to be undertaken: and that ſo much of <hi>Germanie</hi> as was alive, or had a being left, after eighteene yeares troubles; ſhould be quite brought to ruine, by a foure moneths pacification indeed, the fates of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> growing now towards a declination, fortune could bring to paſse no greater thing for them, then the diſcord of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Nothing could happen more acceptable to the Eagles, a good while ſince beginning to ſtoope, then to be enabled to breake thoſe in pieces, being ſeparated, whom they ſtood in feare of, being united; and now to beguile, with the pretext of a deceitfull peace, thoſe whom hitherto they could not conquer with force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Armes. And it was an act of no ſmall merit, with one daſh of a Pen to disband ſuch huge Armies; to diſsolve ſo many Leagues made with <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and ſo ſolemnly ſworne; to turne the mightiest Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie they had, into friends; in ſtead of adverſaries, to get aſſistants; to cauſe the <hi>Germane</hi> Faith to be traduced amongst forraine Nations, and esteemed
<pb facs="tcp:18364:23"/> perfidiouſneſſe: and in a word, to bring matters to that paſſe, that whilest they ſhould ſingly fight, they ſhould be ſingly vanquiſhed; and that thoſe who were mightier then others, ſhould enjoy no other privilege, but that of <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> to be the first, to be ſaved for a time, and the laſt to be devoured in the end.</p>
            <p>The most illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> was taken in, to have a part in this Treatie, as one though ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in ſtrength, yet inferiour in honourable atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; who, whether through ſome kinde of emulation, or rather envie of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Victories, I know not, when he ſaw he could not attaine an equall ſhare of honour with them, choſe rather to be an Enemie, and an Vndoer, then a fellow-ſharer and a Debtor to thoſe that were his defenders: And by this meanes, this League was tempered with ſo much the more diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to him; in regard, that howſoever things fell out, he was ſure, that by helping and aſſiſting others, he ſhould derive the whole weight of the <hi>Germane</hi> Warre upon himſelfe and his ſubjects. Certainely, nothing could happen more ſatisfactorie to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours deſires, then to withdraw that maſſie burthen of Warre, under which his Countreyes did long ſince even gaſpe and groane, and to lay the greatest part thereof upon the ſhoulders of the principall Elector; making this undoubted inference to himſelfe, that whether he were conquered, or did conquer, he ſhould both wayes triumph over his Enemies. So the Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation long laboured for, being at the last obtained, to the end, that he might oblige all the particular Princes by private benefites, and by participation of
<pb facs="tcp:18364:24"/> ſpoiles turne Enemies into friends, he beſtowed upon the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> (beſides the Revenues of the Church, uſurped by him for the ſpace of above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres) the Marquiſat of <hi>Luſatia;</hi> and upon his ſonne, the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Magdeburgh;</hi> upon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the Prince <hi>Palatines</hi> Electorſhip, and the Citie of <hi>Donawerth;</hi> upon the Prince of <hi>Brandeburgh,</hi> the reverſion of the Inheritance of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meranie;</hi> and upon the Prince of <hi>Lunenburgh,</hi> that of the Duchie of <hi>Brunſwick;</hi> and hath granted unto the Dukes of <hi>Mechelburgh,</hi> peaceable poſſeſſion of their Countrey, which they had formerly obtained by the <hi>Swediſh</hi> power. He hath taken unto himſelfe the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditarie right to the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Provinces united to it, <hi>Sileſia, Moravia, &amp;c.</hi> as alſo the Supreme Authoritie, in judging Controverſies of matters Spirituall and Temporall, and the particular Dominion of <hi>Philipsbourgh.</hi> He hath retained in his hands for the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> the abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over all the Armies of <hi>Germanie;</hi> and for his younger ſonne, the Biſhoprick of <hi>Halberſtad:</hi> And for the other Princes, as they ſeemed inferiour, though not in right, yet in power (as the <hi>Palatines,</hi> the <hi>Haſſians,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi>) he commanded, that ſome of them ſhould proſtrate themſelves as humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, to obtaine mercie; and others he put into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret List of proſcribed men, and excluded from all hope of pardon, or benefit of the <hi>Amneſtia;</hi> induced thereunto by no ſtronger motive then this, that with the eſtates and ſpoiles of the diſpoſseſsed, he might reward thoſe who had either formerly done him, or lately promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:18364:24"/> him their faithfull ſervice. The forces of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire being by this meanes united, he denounced a moſt deadly Warre againſt the <hi>French,</hi> under pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering <hi>Lorraine;</hi> and againſt the <hi>Swediſh,</hi> under colour of vindicating the <hi>Germane</hi> libertie: moved thereunto by no other conſideration, but becauſe thoſe two Kingdomes had hitherto cast in the way fatall rubbes, to hinder the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Greatneſse and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Monarchie.</p>
            <p>They ſay, that the <hi>Roman Triumviri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dion. Hiſtor. lib. 46. p. 335.</note> to the end that they might purchaſe the favour of the people unto their proſcription, (a thing before that time not heard of) did draw on the great men, partly by the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of the ſlaine, partly by the great Offices and Priesthoods of the dead; that they obliged the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with the Patrimonies of the conquered, and with proviſions of Victuals to be ſupplyed from the Cities, without Money: that they fined the Citizens at a Tenth of their Countrey Mannors and Farmes, and at a halfe part of their other Revenues; recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it as a ſpeciall favour done to thoſe, of whom a tenth part of their Revenue was ſo exacted, though they had not ſo much as a tenth part of their eſtate left.</p>
            <p>But this furie was confined within particular Walls; the bounds of one Citie, did preſcribe limits to theſe ſlaughters; and the ſafetie of all, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with the butcherie of a few. Here, all the Citizens and Subjects, all the Provinces are in the ſame danger; no Citie, no Countrey, no Citizen is
<pb facs="tcp:18364:25"/> exempt from the miſerie of Warre; no corner of all <hi>Germanie,</hi> where the Rapines of Souldiers have not acceſſe: The Confederates, as well as the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, are oppreſſed with exceſſive Contributions; and as if in this eighteene yeeres Warre, bloud enough were not yet ſhed in <hi>Germanie,</hi> the Armes that are ſtill bloudie with the ſlaughter of our friends and allyes, are tranſported into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Sweden.</hi> And yet notwithstanding, what labour ſoever had beene uſed by mans industrie, and whatſoever Envie can endeavour for the deſtruction of Innocents, the juſtice of the common Cauſe remaines invincible; there hath hitherto neither wanted ſucceſſe to things ill deſigned, nor an expected event to things very ill undertaken; but the execution of this Peace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines as unhappie, as the Treatie thereof was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. So perpetually true is that Maxime of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, That fortune is anſwerable to the deſignes, the iſſue conformable to the inventions, and ill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the worſt to the counſeller. Neither is it to be thought ſtrange, that ſo unluckie and ſo unjuſt a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification hath rather kindled a Warre, then quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it; when as the authors of it aymed onely at this, to preferre their private ends before the publike good, to purchaſe their owne ſecuritie with the ruine of others, and make havocke of the ſafetie of all, for the quiet of a few. And ſo factious ſpirits being drawne into contrarie wayes, in ſtead of an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Peace came forth a particular tranſaction, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable to the Emperour, diſgracefull to the
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:18364:25"/> 
               <hi>Saxon,</hi> trecherous to the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> to them that were excluded, voide; and in the cenſure of Strangers, moſt ſhamefull; and as well in regard of them that contracted it, as on their behalfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom it was contracted, of no force or vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie at all.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The firſt Nullitie of the Treatie on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours part: firſt, becauſe treating con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Lands exceedeth the power of the Emperour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or firſt, to let that paſſe, that a few Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> who in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe are not Iudges, but parties, cannot at any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meeting deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the affaires of the Empire, nor debate at their pleaſure, in a Conventicle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18364:26"/> at <hi>Prague,</hi> Controverſies which are onely to be decided in the generall Aſſemblies of the Empire, nor to conclude upon a Peace concerning the tranquillitie of the Chriſtian World, within the ſecret Chambers of one Citie: and in a word, out of a corner of one Kingdome, to denounce a deadly Warre againſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Princes, Dominions, and Kingdomes. Certaine it is, by the opinion of the Doctors of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> ſide, That the Emperour cannot eſtabliſh a lawfull and firme League with Heretickes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a condition, as to grant unto them the Lands and Rights belonging to the Church, lately uſurped by them, and free exerciſe of their Hereſie in the Empire: So, amongſt others, did <hi>Iacobus Simandra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tractat. tom. <hi>11.</hi> p. <hi>11.</hi> p. <hi>181.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of <hi>Pace,</hi> teach a good while ſince, in his Booke of Catholicke Inſtruction, <hi>cap.</hi> 46. <hi>n.</hi> 52. where hee ſaith, <q>That this doth alſo appertaine to the puniſhment and hatred of theſe Heretickes <hi>(meaning the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans)</hi> That faith or promiſe made
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18364:26"/> unto them is not to bee kept, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it be confirmed by oath: <hi>And a little after:</hi> There can be no commerce nor peace with heretikes, and that therefore faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them, though confirmed by oath, ought by no meanes to bee kept: <hi>And hee addes further,</hi> This is often ſaid by us, and yet it is neceſſary to bee unceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly itterated, and not to be ſilenced as long as that name of peace is pretended.</q> So <hi>Conradus Brunius</hi> profeſſor of the law, and Chancelor of <hi>Otho Truchſeſius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Auſpurg</hi> at the ſame time, when the tranſaction of <hi>Paſſaw</hi> was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Empire, in his third Booke <hi>de Hereticis c.</hi> 15. puts this queſtion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tractat tom.</hi> 11. p. 305.</note> 
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Whether contracts, agreements, lawes and reſcripts, whereby heretike, doe obtaine peace and ſecuritie, be of any force or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditie, ſo as if any man ſhall offend them, bee be guilty of the breach of ſuch a peace? Alſo who they bee, that are permitted to reforme Churches, adminiſter and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence, to poſſeſſe lands and eſtates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Churches, and Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18364:27"/> Iuriſdiction to bee ſuſpended againſt them? And hee anſwereth expreſly, that ſuch contracts, agreements, &amp;c. are of no validitie: And that it is an unjuſt and blaſphemous condition, whereby permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is given to Heretikes to teach their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: And in the end of the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee addeth, At this day no peace can be of force which is made with Heretikes, upon this condition they are not to bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. That, that peace is abhominable and to be abhorred, which is is made upon this condition that thoſe which offend them ſhould bee condemned to have broken the peace: That on the contrary, all Divine and Humane lawes would have them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſtinguiſhed. And ſo lately <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Becanus</hi> Doctor of Divinitie and Profeſſor at <hi>Mentz,</hi> in a diſputation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faith to be held with Heretikes, <hi>c. 10. p. 88.</hi> and ſo forward teacheth, That,<note place="margin">Set forth at <hi>Mentz.</hi> 1607. and reprinted, 1619.</note> that Libertie granted, or Accord made touching Religion, whereby it is freely permitted to a man to bee a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or a Lutheran, or a Calviniſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18364:27"/> unlawfull, and repugnant to Gods Commandement; And is not to bee tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated otherwiſe then for ſome time, and for the avoyding of ſome greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: And <hi>p. 94.</hi> Let all men know, that although ſuch kind of men may have obtained ſome ſuch thing by ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Reſcript or Contract, yet it is of no force.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo a Booke very lately ſet forth touching the concluſion of a peace made betwixt the Catholikes and the Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to the confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the Commandment and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Superiors at <hi>Dilling,</hi> 1629. and approoved by the Doctors profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Law in the Archdukes Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>Freiburgh,</hi> and added by way of Commentary to that Edict of Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſixth of <hi>March</hi> 1629. doth in many places profeſſedly teach, <q>
                  <hi>That ſuch tranſ-actions or agreements of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes with Heretikes and Lutherans, are by the Law it ſelfe voyd, unlawfull, and unluckie:</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And hee alleadgeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18364:28"/> reaſons of this aſſertion, whereof for brevities ſake I will onely point at the chiefe.</p>
            <p>His firſt is, That ſuch a Treaty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the limits of ſecular, yea, even of Imperiall Iuriſdiction: <hi>So hee teacheth,</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> q. <hi>25.</hi> n. <hi>20.</hi> p. <hi>114. in theſe words:</hi> 
               <q>The Emperors neither would nor could decree by their authoritie, that certaine Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Benefices poſſeſſed by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſioniſt, ought to be left unto them: And <hi>p. 122.</hi> It exceeds all ſecular, yea, and the ſupreme Caeſarean power, to determine that Church lands and benefices being tranſlated from lawfull Eccleſiaſticall Prelats and beneficed men to Lay perſons uncapable thereof, and averſe from the Catholike religion, ought to remaine in their poſſeſſion: the Iuriſdiction over their eſtates and perſons, being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the reſt of the Biſhops and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, as to the uſe and exerciſe thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His ſecond reaſon which is, becauſe a Catholike Prince cannot by any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes bind himſelfe to tolerate Hereſie,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18364:28"/> is declared in the ſame Chapter,</hi> q. <hi>26.</hi> n. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>133. in theſe words:</hi> 
               <q>To ſpeake abſolutely (caſe of neceſſitie excepted) it is unlawfull for a Magiſtrate, and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious againſt God to tolerate Hereſie: <hi>And a little after</hi> n. <hi>30.</hi> If in ſome caſe and ſome time it may be lawfull to tolerate Hereſie; yet it is not lawfull for any man to bind himſelfe by promiſes or oathes to tolerate it; becauſe by the law <hi>l. 5. ff. de pactis,</hi> That contract and agreement is void whereby any man is invited or drawn on to offend: <hi>And</hi> n. <hi>31.</hi> Though at ſome time a Catholike Magiſtrate in a caſe of extreame neceſſitie may prudently bind himſelfe to tolerate his Heretike ſubjects for a certaine time; yet that ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhould bee made perpetuall, it can ſcarſe at any time bee lawfull:</q> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe reaſon immediately followeth; <q>Becauſe a Magiſtrate cannot permit or promiſe a toleration of Hereſie in his Country, unleſſe it bee to avoid a greater miſchiefe from the Common Wealth: But there can no miſchiefe happen more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18364:29"/> and pernicious to a Common Wealth, then if Hereſie bee ſo brought in, that it may at no time bee lawfull to prohibit, or remove it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third reaſon is there alleadged,</hi> q. <hi>28.</hi> n. <hi>47.</hi> 
               <q>Becauſe the authoritie and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Pope ought to interpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a league can be lawfully made with Heretikes for the tolerating of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For whereas ſuch a league doth tend to the detriment of the Church, and doth indirectly concerne ſpiritual matter, that is to ſay, permitting of a falſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therfore nothing ought herein to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the Pope not being firſt conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with:</q> Now the Treaty of <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> and the Pacification of <hi>Prague</hi> were never approved by the Pope, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Iudgement of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Doctors are of no moment and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie:<note place="margin">2. Becauſe this tranſ-action is founded upon the Treaty of <hi>Paſſaw.</hi>
               </note> Which ought ſo much the more to bee conſidered, becauſe the Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of <hi>Prague</hi> in the principall parts thereof is founded upon the Tranſ-action of <hi>Paſſaw:</hi> for ſo ſaith
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18364:29"/> the firſt Article in the frontiſpiece expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>As for the poſſeſsions of the Church medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately depending of the holy Empire, let the conſtitution of the Treaty of</hi> Paſſaw <hi>remain unviolated.</hi> But by the doctrine of the ſame Doctors, in the Preface of the book formerly cited, &amp;c. <hi>v. q.</hi> 25. <hi>p.</hi> 115.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The peace of Religion concluded with the <hi>Lutherans</hi> at <hi>Nurenbergh,</hi> 1552. and confirmed at <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> 1555. is no finall accord, no generall or pragmaticall, nor perpetuall ſanction or tranſ-action, but onely a tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie contract, agreement, and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which as it was introduced and eſtabliſhed by the Emperors authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with the conſent of divers States of the Empire, ſo by the like power of a ſucceeding Emperor the greater part of the Princes of the Empire giving their votes therunto, it may bee repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</q> Yea, and even in it ſelfe it is of no great validitie, being by force of armes extracted from <hi>Charles V.</hi> and upon ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſsity granted to the <hi>Lutherans</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand I.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18364:30"/>
            <p>For ſo the agreement of peace often cited <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 109. <hi>Anno</hi> 1554. ſaith: <q>When <hi>Charles V.</hi> did make a pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie tranſaction with the Confeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, the State of the affaires in the Empire was ſo troubled, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror knew not what counſell to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and therefore confeſſed, that hee being preſſed with adverſities and hard conditions, did grant peace to the Heretikes, and did commend the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate ſtate of the Catholikes in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> to Gods good pleaſure, untill a a more fortunate time and occaſion did offer it ſelfe.</q> 
               <hi>Iohannes Paulus Windeck</hi> taught the ſame doctrine a good while ſince, in his deliberation touching the rooting out of Heretikes, printed at <hi>Colen</hi> with the leave and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Caeſarean Majeſtie, <hi>art.</hi> 3. in the anſwer to the 4. Objection <hi>p.</hi> 324. <q>That which the Emperour did by this agreement of peace grant to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, hee was compelled to doe it by extreame neceſsitie: For the <hi>Turke</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18364:30"/> at that time hovering over <hi>Auſtria,</hi> it was neceſſarie for him to gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther al his ſtrength from al parts round about him.</q> Beſides, although the Ttranſ-action of this peace had beene moſt free, yet according to the opinion of the foreſaid Doctors, there was no intereſt in the poſſeſsions of the Church granted by it to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſuſpenſion of the Biſhops intereſt in them. And ſo doth the Booke of the concluſion of the peace expreſſely teach, <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 30. <hi>n.</hi> 4. 5. 6. 7. When it ſaith: <q>That by the tranſaction of <hi>Paſſaw</hi> no right or authoritie was granted to the Heretickes of detayning or uſurping the poſſeſsions of the Church, or teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurg</hi> in the Empire againſt the Catholike truth; but they onely obtained a ſuſpenſion of Epiſcopall Iuriſdiction and of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons belonging to Catholikes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet more expreſſely <hi>n.</hi> 5.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Catholikes doe poſſeſſe the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and the exerciſe of their Religi-
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18364:31"/> by their proper and ancient right; but Confeſsioniſts who have no juſt title to them, have intereſt in them onely by detaining them; and beſides, and contrary to all right and juſtice doe enjoy that permiſsion and indulgence granted unto them, not without the prejudice and damage of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes: Yea, and they hold the exerciſe of their Hereſie onely by priviledge, and a ſpeciall or extraordinary kind of right: for it is manifeſt that the confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurg</hi> was received in the Empire by ſuch a ſpeciall and extraordinary right,<note place="margin">L. Quod ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò C. de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Ius ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiam non trahendum.</note> and by favour and indulgence, whereas it is rejected e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where elſe. Whereupon hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly inferreth by way of <hi>Corollary,</hi> That the <hi>Lutherans</hi> doe without cauſe complaine, that the Catholikes doe call the Confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurg</hi> a meere toleration; when as it is certaine, that it hath beene divers times condemned in the Empire, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver approoved, but onely tolerated;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18364:31"/> and that no injurie is herein done to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> who can ſhew no title or evidence for their poſſeſsion or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, but onely force and intruſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: When as on the contrary ſide the Catholikes, though they bee ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by the Preſcription of a moſt ancient poſſeſsion, yet for the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant juſtification of their right, they can make their titles and eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces appeare to all.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Moreover, although the Treaty of <hi>Paſſaw</hi> were of undoubted authoritie, yet by the opinion of the Catholikes, the Proteſtants have very many waies violated that ſanction, and as much as in them lay, have utterly abrogated it: In regard that not onely after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it <hi>Anno</hi> 1552. and 1555. they did by force and intruſion, throwing out the Catholikes, take poſſeſsion of three Archbiſhopricks, fourteene Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, and above three hundred Church-livings and Monaſteries (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which the <hi>Dominicans</hi> alone are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18364:32"/> ſaid to have loſt above ſeventie) as that Declaration of the Peace of Religion concluded betwixt the Catholikes and Proteſtant Princes, and Nobles of the Empire, printed as it ſeemeth at <hi>Munchin</hi> 1629. in <hi>Quarto.</hi> particularly ſheweth; but alſo by very many new Doctrines brought in touching the Vbiquitie of <hi>Chriſts Body, Free-will,</hi> the <hi>Maſſe</hi> or <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> they have ſo altered the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Auſpurg</hi> ſet forth in the Booke of Concord 1580. That at this day there are no Proteſtants found in the world, who doe ſtill Adhere to the true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> as it was preſented by their Anceſtors to <hi>Charles V. Anno</hi> 1530. Beſides that, many Proteſtants lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Doctrine of the Confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> have in very many Articles imbraced the opinions of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Zvinglius:</hi> From whence it appeares as cleere as the Noone day, that ſince the Peace of Religion 1552. was onely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thoſe that profeſſe the true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> and that all the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18364:32"/> Proteſtants are in many points departed from it; and many of them have decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Hereſie of <hi>Calvin:</hi> They have by the judgement of the Catholikes, long ſince deprived themſelves of all grace and priviledges granted unto them by the Peace of Religion; and have made themſelves unworthy of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toleration: as the Booke of the Concluſion of Peace prooveth every point at large <hi>c.</hi> 10. and 11. <hi>q.</hi> 81. and 82. <hi>p.</hi> 574. 581. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Neither indeede did the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Emperours ever deny,<note place="margin">3. By the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> that it was out of their power and juriſdiction to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing in matter of Religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Decrees of the holy Canons, or Councels. So without doubt did the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand. I.</hi> confeſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly at the breaking up of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of <hi>Auſpurgh, Anno</hi> 1559. the 13.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1559</label> day of <hi>Iune,</hi> in theſe words: <q>It is beyond the compaſſe of all Secular power, yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Supreame Imperiall Majeſtie it ſelfe, that the poſſeſſions of the Church
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18364:33"/> ſhould be tranſlated from lawfull Prelates and devolved unto Lay and Hereticall perſons, and remaine in their poſſeſsion.</q> So alſo <hi>Rodulph. II.</hi> When he granted libertie of Religion to the Proteſtant States of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratory Letter of the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1606.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1606</label> ſaith, <hi>That as well thoſe Articles which belong to Religion and the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Order, as the reſt, are thus to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, ſo farre forth as they bee not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Oath given to the States at his Coronation, for the defence of the Catholike Religion, and extirpation of Hereſie.</hi> And for this cauſe the Emperour <hi>Charles V.</hi> publiſhed a generall revocation of all thoſe things which hee confeſſed, hee ſometimes granted to Heretikes againſt his conſcience, dated at <hi>Bruxels</hi> 19. <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1555</label> 1555. which was a little after the Peace of Religion granted by <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand I.</hi> at <hi>Nurenberg</hi> and <hi>Auſpurgh;</hi> with no other intention but this, that at one and the ſame time, hee might wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly by himſelfe diſanull that liberty,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18364:33"/> which being compelled by his brother, he had formerly publiſhed. Which they doe at this day ſuppoſe to bee made the more ſacred and ſolemne, becauſe after the publication of the <hi>Councell of Trent</hi> 1564.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1564</label> by the Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth, which revoked all things that were granted in prejudice of the ſaid Councell: All Contracts, Agreements, and Ordinances, in thoſe points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are contrary to the Decrees of the Councell, are by Law revoked, made voyd, and diſanulled; and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the rules and limits of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and ſo are judged to be.<note place="margin">4. Experience of things paſt.</note> And this is the reaſon why notwithſtanding all cautions, aſſurances, and Capitulations whatſoever made to the contrary, the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> ever have proceeded, and ſtill doe in the reformation of Religion, and extirpation of Hereſie with open force, in the <hi>Palatinate, Bohemia, Hungary, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe they believe all ſuch Agreements and Capitulations to bee fruſtrate, and voyd in Law; and that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18364:34"/> they can bee confirmed by no Oath or Contract whatſoever. And that we may not depart any further from our inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diſcourſe. <hi>Ferdinand II.</hi> then Arch-Duke of <hi>Gratz,</hi> now Emperor, although at his Coronation <hi>Anno</hi> 1599.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1599</label> hee had fully promiſed to the Nobles of the Confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the three Hereditary Provinces of <hi>Styria, Carinthia,</hi> and <hi>Carniola,</hi> liberty of conſcience. Yet preſently upon it, in the very beginning of his Government by a publike Edict, he drave all the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes out of his Dominions, and in a ſolemne reſolution given unto the States of thoſe three Provinces at <hi>Gratz,</hi> the laſt of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1599. he openly profeſſed, That thoſe Heretikes could alledge no priviledge either in holy Scriptures, or in any Law of God or man, for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion. And the ſame Emperour although by the ſacred Charter of <hi>Rodulph II.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1609</label> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1609. ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proviſion was made for the States of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18364:34"/> have free Exerciſe of their Religion of both kinds; yet aſſoone as he tooke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Government of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hee demoliſhed divers of the Proteſtants Churches to the ground, and ſhut up the Inhabitants in priſon: Whereupon ſoone after aroſe thoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full troubles in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> And not long after that, <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. though,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1621</label> when hee was advanced to the Empire, hee had promiſed the States of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne agreement made betwixt them, that if they would leave the Party of the <hi>Prince Palatine Fredericke,</hi> hee would religiouſly preſerve all their Rights and Priviledges, both Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall: Yet for all this, when the <hi>Prince Palatine</hi> was diſpoſſeſſed, he did preſently after with all the ſtrength hee could, contrary to his covenants and promiſes, every where abrogate the Profeſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh.</hi> And although in the yeare 1619.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1619</label> at his Election at <hi>Franckford</hi> by a new agreement, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Articles of the Emperours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18364:35"/> Capitulation, hee had bound himſelfe to the <hi>Electors</hi> and Proteſtant Princes of the Empire, by a particular Oath for the defence of the Peace of Religion in <hi>Germany:</hi> yet notwithſtanding, when hee had gotten the upper hand in the Empire,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1629</label> hee did by the Edict of reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution proſcribe all the poſſeſsions of the Church, that were in the <hi>Lutherans</hi> juriſdiction, and prohibited the Exerciſe of the Religion of <hi>Auſpurgh</hi> in them; which gave the occaſion of this moſt bloudy Warre in <hi>Germany.</hi> And though now,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1635</label> the neceſsity of his affaires urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to it, and being ſpent with Warre; he hath made a Peace for forty yeares with the moſt powerfull of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Yet hath hee not layd aſide his former purpoſe of caſting out all his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries under the name of Heretikes, and of ſtripping them of all their ſtrength, under the colour of reſtoring the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions of the Church, and of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other Peace in <hi>Germany,</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18364:35"/> Catholikes; holding himſelfe to this reſolution, That Catholikes can hold no firme Peace with Heretikes. That this was the intention of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Imperiall Majeſtie, it was in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſhew declared by a Booke made by his commandment at the <hi>Dyet of Ratisbone,</hi> and publiſhed a little after at <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> in the yeare 1630.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1630</label> under this Title <hi>The foundations of the Peace happily laid in the ſacred Roman Empire, by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of Pope Vrban</hi> 8. <hi>and by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Ferdinand</hi> 2. <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, That no firme Peace can be hoped for in <hi>Germany,</hi> but by the reſtitution of Religion, and the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Catholikes into their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate and condition: But if at any time for the avoyding of a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, Peace had beene granted unto Heretikes by the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> it was done but for a time, to the end, that ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter occaſion being ſhortly after offered, the whole burthen and weight of a Warre might be turned upon them. So
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18364:36"/> did <hi>Iohanne, Paulus Windeck</hi> clearely confeſſe not long ſince in the Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation above cited, <hi>p.</hi> 414. in theſe words,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1619</label> 
               <hi>The Tranſ-action which Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes have ſometimes made with Sectaries, they have made them ayming at this end, that other buſineſſes, being diſpatched in the meane time, afterwards they might make and manage this Warre wholly againſt Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and turne the whole Weight thereof upon their backes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1629</label> For ſo doth <hi>Peter Ribadeneira</hi> teach, that Chriſtian diſsimulation is to bee u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in his Booke <hi>de Principe, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>p.</hi> 178. If great dangers bee feared; and <hi>Becanus</hi> in his diſputation of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping faith with Heretickes, <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 89. ſaith, <hi>If the Lutheran Religion cannot bee conveniently hindred, or driven out of a State, but with a greater damage to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, then it may bee tolerated for ſome time, untill a more fortunate ſeaſon, or occaſion doe offer it ſelfe, as that Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Peace teacheth,</hi> n. 1609. And that this conſideration of concluding a Peace
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18364:36"/> for a time was obſerved in that Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Prague,</hi> the buſineſſe it ſelfe declares:<note place="margin">5. Out of the Treaty of <hi>Prague</hi> it ſelfe.</note> For that Tranſ-action though at the firſt appearance it doe ſeeme ſomewhat the more ignominious, and diſadvantageous to the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, whereby not onely that Sacred Edict of the Emperour, touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the poſſeſsions of the Church of the ſixth of <hi>March</hi> 1629. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publiſhed againſt the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> is wholly abrogated, but alſo very many grievances of the Proteſtants exhibited at the <hi>Dyet of Ratisbone</hi> 1630.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1630</label> and in the Convention of <hi>Lipſich</hi> are refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, according to their owne deſire,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> yet it doth ſecretly make the Emperour Maſter over all his enemies; yea, and ſole Lord and Maſter in the Empire. Whileſt amongſt other things it giveth him Hereditary right over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> the free diſpoſition of the Colledge of Electors, and Imperiall Chamber; abſolute command over all the Armies of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18364:37"/> and in concluſion, a plenary cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of all ſuits and controverſies, which ſhould hereafter ariſe touching matter of Religion, and this pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that what he ſeemed to grant with his left hand, hee preſently takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with his right, and whileſt he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth a Peace of a few yeares to the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> hee graſpes into his hand all the Forces of the whole Empire, being ready to employ them againſt the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> at his pleaſure, upon the firſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, as hath beene done heretofore.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18364:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The ſecond Nullity of the Treaty on the part of the Duke of <hi>Saxony:</hi> Firſt, becauſe that by this meanes the ſtrength of the Proteſtants is utterly ruined.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore the Princes of the ſmaler States being excluded from the <hi>Amneſtia,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded a League with the moſt powerfull head of the Proteſtants, by which hee did not onely joyne the greateſt part of the great men to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but alſo (which was the Principall thing of all) he disjoyned and ſeparated the moſt powerfull of his enemies; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this as a moſt certaine ſubtiltie to elude the ſtrength of his adverſaries, if he might be able to deſtroy thoſe being drawne aſunder, for whom he was too weake being gathered together. That
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18364:38"/> forces united are ſtronger then divided, and that a common danger is to be kept off by concord, reaſon hath dictated to all men, and experience hath confirmed to the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>The Emperour who hath hitherto beene too weake, when their Armies were joyned together, could find no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer remedy then the ſeparation of them; and whileſt hee doth with mutuall ſlaughters deſtroy his adverſaries, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now growne mightier by the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and diſcords of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> turnes the faults of his enemies into the hope of a Victory. This is the ancient cunning of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> having beene with happy ſucceſſe practiſed a good while ſince by <hi>Charles V.</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand I. Iohannes Paulus Windeck,</hi> is a domeſticall witneſſe hereof in his deliberation touching the rooting out of Heretikes, <hi>p.</hi> 412. and ſo forward: whoſe words ought to bee to the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> decretorie, when he ſaith: <hi>For the driving out of Sectaries is required.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18364:38"/> Firſt, a league and aſſociation of Catholike Princes. Secondly, the occaſion is not to be neglected, and that is, when the Proteſtants money is exhauſted. Thirdly, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes may the more eaſily ſuppreſſe the Sectaries, let them by the invention of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers cauſes and pretences, pull them aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one from another, and that was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by</hi> Charles V. <hi>very much to his benefit. Fourthly, let Catholikes get in forraine aides to their aſsiſtance, for the vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sectaries: and on the other ſide, let them uſe all the caution that may be, that the Sectaries get no aſsiſtance from forrainers.</hi> All theſe things were moſt exactly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, in the Pacification of <hi>Prague;</hi> When as the League of Catholikes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in name taken away by it, under the Title of Empire was framed an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation of moſt of the Princes with the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> and preſently after, the ſtrongeſt of the Proteſtants, the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> the <hi>Heſsians,</hi> and they of <hi>Wirtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> &amp;c. were drawne away from the reſt. And leaſt hereafter they ſhould call
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18364:39"/> in aide from Forreiners for the defence of their cauſe; under pretext of Peace, Warre was denounced againſt the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>Swedes,</hi> with a moſt calamitous deluſion of the <hi>Saxon:</hi> Who, whileſt hee ſeekes a private Peace rather then a publique; whileſt hee laboured for the friendſhip of one man, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the friendſhip of all; whileſt fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a Warre, hitherto unhappy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, he laboureth to transferre it to Forreiners and his friends; hee not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wary of it, did (as the Hiſtorian long ſince reported of <hi>Marſeilles</hi>) for feare of a Warre,<note place="margin">Florus Hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> fall into a Warre: A Warre ſo much the more unjuſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe undertaken againſt Brethren, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Allies, againſt Fellow-profeſſors of the ſame faith and beliefe; by him who had no rightfull power or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over them.<note place="margin">2. Becauſe the Treating of a common Peace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the power of the Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For I pray you, By what authoritie doth the moſt illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony,</hi> who in this buſineſſe is neither Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of the Empire nor Procurator for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18364:39"/> the Proteſtants, nor Vmpire for Forrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, alone by himſelfe take upon him to determine the controverſies of the whole Empire? By what power doth hee endeavour to alter, or abrogate in a private corner, things long ſince deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the publique Aſſemblies, touching both the Religious, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Peace? By what right can hee limit to the ſpace of forty yeares, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Religion granted to all the Proteſtants for ever? Why doth hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone make an accord touching the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Colledge of Electors, touching the reformation of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chamber, touching military affaires, and the contribution of all the States of the Empire, to the prejudice of moſt men, and againſt the Will of all? By what licence or power doth hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to transferre Cities, Provinces, Principalities; Subjects neither to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor any body elſe, and to bring them under the private command of the Emperour? Doth it belong to his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18364:40"/> charge to make <hi>Bohemia, Sileſia, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> Hereditary to the <hi>Auſtrians?</hi> And <hi>Luſatia</hi> to himſelfe? To take away the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and Dutchy of <hi>Wirtembergh,</hi> from their proper Lords, and <hi>Philipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh,</hi> which was in all ſacred right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to her owne Biſhop? And in a word, to arme all the forces of <hi>Germany</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> for the recovery of <hi>Lorraine?</hi> As if hee had any authoritie over forraine States, or as if he being circumſcribed and limited himſelfe, could preſcribe lawes to them, over whom as being his equalls, and his betters, he hath no command: Let him rather blame himſelfe for being ſo ill adviſed, as under a pretext of Peace, to approove all the former Injuries, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations of the <hi>Auſtrians:</hi> And for that hee alone hath by the connivence of a foure moneths Treaty eſtabliſhed thoſe things which they were not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world unto by almoſt twenty yeares War. The truth is, to the end that the forepaſſed actions of the Emperour
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18364:40"/> might have ſome title of right, they muſt bee confirmed by a Triumvirall pacification; and that things done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to law and right,<note place="margin">L. <hi>54.</hi> D. de regulis juris. Nemo plus juris ad ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um transfere poteſt, quam ipſe haberet.</note> might carry ſome ſhew of Iuſtice, they were to be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by a publique conſpiracie: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nevertheleſſe the Emperour had no addition at all of authoritie, nor the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> the leaſt increaſe of profit.</p>
            <p>For by this Tranſ-action of <hi>Prague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Becauſe this Treaty of the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> is unprofitable and hurtfull to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</note> neither was his Dignitie increaſed, nor his Iurisdiction honorably enlarged; nor the Religion whereof he taketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be a Prince, and a Defender, any where propagated, much leſſe firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed: But on the contrary, of a free Prince, and one that hath ſo often triumphed over his enemies, he is made a Commiſſary of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> His Territories are become as a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke to the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> and <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> the profeſsion of the Confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh</hi> under ſo noble a Protector, was thruſt out of doores in the moſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18364:41"/> and beſt Provinces of the Empire, and was ſent away and confined within the bounds of <hi>Saxony</hi> and the Ocean. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the moſt miſerable of all, who did formerly draw from the Victories and toiles of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> his life, and ſafety of his Dignitie and Country being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards brought ſo low, that not being able to pay, he had rather turne bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, then be indebted, doth at this day alone beare the whole burthen of a moſt calamitous Warre, as being not onely ſhut out of the principall part of his Territories; but even doubtfull and uncertaine of his life and ſafety. Surely by the moſt juſt law of requiting like for like, he ought to impute unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the prejudice, hee feeleth through his owne fault; and he that had provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armes to be enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, being almoſt quite ſpent and tyred with them, doth faint and ſinke under them.</p>
            <p>But is that ſo? Are the liberty of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and thoſe glorious Titles of Peace
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18364:41"/> made a colour for a wicked conſpiracie? Surely amongſt perfidious and perjured perſons, it is an ordinary thing under the pretext of confidencie to foment a Warre: Neither did any man ever covet anothers ſervitude, or his owne domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but he would uſe thoſe faire and ſpecious names. For if the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> did intend to eſtabliſh a true Peace in the Empire, or a peaceable tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie in his Country; Why did he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily ſuffer ſo many Princes, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny States of his owne party, partners in one and the ſame cauſe, and rebellion, to be excluded out of the <hi>Amneſtia?</hi> If he had a purpoſe to reſtore the Majeſtie, and Dignitie of the ſacred Empire, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Liberty of it to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſplendor and glory: Why did hee ſo ſhamefully reject ſo many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Kings ſo valiantly defending the <hi>German</hi> Liberty, as well within the Empire as without, from having their part in the common pacification, and ſend them away out of the bounds of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18364:42"/> 
               <hi>Germany</hi> like ſlaves or drudges, without any manner of mention of the leaſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at all? If by this ſacred Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action hee endeavoured to bring this to paſſe, that Iuſtice being reſtored to her integritie, and made to flouriſh againe throughout the Empire, all the States and Citizens thereof might enjoy their equall right and common quiet. Why did he leave the affaires of the Imperiall Chamber and holy Conſiſtory, from whence all the troubles and diſſentions have hitherto ſprung, undecided, and to bee decided meerely at the Emperours pleaſure and determination? If hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by this Tranſ-action to redeeme the Peace of Religion, the Libertie of teaching the Confeſsion of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> throughout the Empire, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo many ſoules (as hee preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.) Why did hee permit the free ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exciſe of their Religion to bee prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſo many thouſands of men in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, Syleſia, Auſtria,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the Biſhoprickes of <hi>Halberſtad</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18364:42"/> 
               <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> ſo many Miniſters and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens being baniſhed for their beliefes ſake, to endure a perpetuall exile out of their native country? If his purpoſe were to eſtabliſh an honeſt, ſolemne, and publike peace, and ſuch a one as ſhould be profitable and honourable to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and all his confederates: Why did he begin with ingratitude the worſt of all vices, in turning his perjured Armes againſt his allies, by whom he had beene once and againe delivered from certaine deſtruction and ruine long ſince ſworne againſt him by the <hi>Auſtrians?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of the <hi>Saxon.</hi>
               </note> For with what title of right can ſo deteſtable a treachery, ſo horrible a treaſon bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed? with what ſhew of Iuſtice can it be cloaked, in which thoſe ſame men, whom you called to your party for their ſafetie, are delivered over by you to them that are ſaved to bee totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye: And thoſe men of whom you (though unworthy) obtained life and preſervation, the ſame being moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily proſcribed, are by you robbed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18364:43"/> of their life and honour: and ſo you make your friends moſt angry with you not onely after, but even becauſe of the benefits received of them by you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiis.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 1.</note> Hee is commonly judged to be an unthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, who either denies himſelfe to have received a benefit, or having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved one, concealeth it; hee is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, that requites it not; but he is moſt unthankefull of all, that hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten it: For the former although they repay not, yet they remaine debtors, and are often brought in time to requite a favour received: This latter can never bee made thankefull, who refuſeth to be a debtor for, much more to requite that hee hath received: But theſe things, as they are effects of an ancienter crime, ſo are they of leſſe note and infamy: A new kind of ingratitude here diſcovers it ſelfe, an abhomination to God, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement to poſterity, and a thing to be owned by <hi>Adraſtia</hi> her ſelfe, which doth not onely not acknowledge, not requite, not thankefully eſteeme a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18364:43"/> received, but for good deeds returne miſchiefes, for good deſerts Injuries, and for favour deſtruction. The moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned King of the <hi>Swedes,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1630</label> 
               <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> ever of a moſt venerable and triumphant memory, did revenge private Injuries by a peculiar Warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Auſtrians:</hi> The Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> then the encourager and leader of the Proteſtants, now the forſaker and betrayer of them, though hee feared the common Enemie, yet hee refuſed a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall joyning in armes, and by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy delaying of time ſuffered <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburgh</hi> to be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Soone after that,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> being vanquiſhed by the whole power of the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> when as being in a manner ſhut up in <hi>Dreſden</hi> hee ſaw himſelfe farre too weake for his Enemies, being then made more wary by his owne danger, then by another mans; Vpon a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Tranſ-action made at <hi>Torgaw</hi> the firſt of <hi>September</hi> 1631.<note place="margin">The Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Torgaw.</hi> 1. <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1631.</note> he called for aide from the moſt renowned King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18364:44"/> he entred with him into a ſociety of armes &amp; Counſels, he delivered up to the <hi>Swedes</hi> the paſſages and forts which were upon the river of <hi>Elbe,</hi> hee offered pay, ammunition, and proviſion of corn neceſſary for his Souldiers, making an Inviolable promiſe and oath, that hee never would accept any peace without their conſent. And ſo by this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of armes being delivered from the preſent danger of death, by the Valour of the <hi>Swedes</hi> (for his owne forces did now begin to gaſpe) hee obtained that moſt famous Victory of <hi>Lipſich</hi> and the preſervation of his rights and territories,<note place="margin">The battell of <hi>Lipſich.</hi> 7. <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1635.</note> and forthwith to ſhew his due thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, hee appointed publike ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to be made for the preſervation of the King, who was now become a triumpher over his Enemies, a defender of his owne and a recoverer of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> libertie; hee ordained the ſeventh day of <hi>September,</hi> being as it were, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to the memory of that Victory, to bee ſolemnely obſerved in all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18364:44"/> Churches of the profeſſors of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and he did celebrate the Proteſtants day of deliverance, gotten by the <hi>Swedes</hi> in Bookes publiſhed through the whole Empire. Shortly after, as the ſpirits of thoſe that are moſt fierce in ſlaughters are many times tender;<note place="margin">Mercur. Gallobelg. tom. <hi>18.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> when the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Caderet</hi> the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Embaſſador under a pretence of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient amitie betweene the Houſes of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Saxony,</hi> endevoured to draw away the <hi>Saxons</hi> from the <hi>Swedes,</hi> he anſwered his Agents nobly and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, That he could not recover the deſperate condition of <hi>Germany,</hi> nor ſave his Country being now in a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtraction by any particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords; that divers examples have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſhowne, that ſuch accords would not effect an univerſall Peace in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> but rather worke greater miſchiefes; Neither if he ſhould make any ſuch, that any colour of excuſe could bee left him before the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant States: But after that glorious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18364:45"/> King did at the battell of <hi>Lutzen</hi> even by his very death triumph over his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note place="margin">The battell of <hi>Lutzen.</hi> 11. <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1632. The skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh at <hi>Nordlingen.</hi> 27. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1634.</note> and that at the skirmiſh of <hi>Nord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingen</hi> the affaires of the <hi>Swedes</hi> did ſeeme by little and little to decline. The Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> who before had ſtirred them all up to armes and rebellion (as he now called it) began to revolt from his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; and ſhortly after by ſecret meſſages, and after that by publike tranſ-actions to make an accord with the Common Enemie; and to purchaſe his owne eſtabliſhment with the ruine of his allies, and his domeſticall peace with making Warre upon ſtrangers. So being circumſcribed within the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Prague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Prague</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the 30. of <hi>May.</hi> 1635.</note> he denounced hoſtile armes againſt them by whom hee had twice or thrice beene delivered from preſent deſtruction, and who by the death of their owne King had preſerved his life, and by the effuſion of their owne, ſaved the ſhedding of the <hi>Saxons</hi> bloud. This great office of exceeding favor was utterly loſt upon them, being
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18364:45"/> beſtowed upon the moſt unthankfull of mortall men, who eſteemed it as the higheſt merit to deſerve worſt of thoſe that had deſerved beſt of them. All good offices came to bee interpreted as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked acts, all loving and friendly deeds as ſo many crimes, and the bloud of them was not ſpared for whom bloud was to be ſhed. Good turnes are requited with ſword and haltars; it is the honour and Dignitie of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Commiſſaries to flye at the throat of their defendors, and to ſet their feete up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the neckes of thoſe they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered. The armies ſent from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are turned againſt them, and the <hi>Saxon</hi> Generalls Exhortation is this:<note n="*" place="margin">The very words (within a very little) of that ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, publiſhed by the Duke of of <hi>Saxony</hi> againſt the <hi>Sweds,</hi> in the Campe of <hi>Schusken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> 19. <hi>October.</hi> 1635.</note> 
               <hi>Fight againſt your brethren, againſt your Allies, againſt the</hi> Lutherans, <hi>againſt thoſe that are governed by the ſame law, and Profeſſors of the ſame Religion with you. Set upon the Churches, the Altars, and the dwelling houſes of your friends with force of armes: Imbrue your ſelves in the bloud of your Kinsfolkes and take away by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18364:46"/> the benefit of their native Countrey from thoſe that bee but halfe right, ſucke and ſpoyle them with your troupes. Let them, who brought life and ſafety to us, bee like baniſhed men excluded from the uſe of fire and water: Let them, who purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Libertie with their bloud, be bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſcattered farre and wide out of the Empire, as ſworne Enemies to peace, and diſturbers of the publike tranquillity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoever ſhall relieve his friend, his patrone, his defender with bread or water, let him be proceeded againſt as guilty of treaſon. Whoſoever ſhall kill, betray, or corrupt his protector or preſerver, let him receive impunitie, money and a garland: (onely not ſuch a one as was give to him that ſaved a Citizen:) Let Libertie bee no more mentioned amongſt military banners, and let that people the conqueror and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of nations, confine it ſelfe within the ſnow and yee of their owne Ocean: and there their Warres being laid aſide and put farre enough from them, and all feare and terror of them being repreſſed; let them live in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18364:46"/> awe and horror of our Eagles.</hi> Theſe are the requitalls of thoſe ſavers and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; this is the reward of thoſe defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: theſe are the thankes and the bounties, whereby a vaſt benefit is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced with more vaſt Injuries.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The third Nullity of the part of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. Firſt, becauſe they made their Warre againſt the Emperour being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to it by the <hi>Saxon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow if theſe Treaties of the <hi>Saxon</hi> againſt the <hi>Swedes</hi> can by no title or colour of right bee defended, as himſelfe late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed: much leſſe can his negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions entred into with the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtants, carry any ſhew of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18364:47"/> excuſe at all. For what did he? When as the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand II.</hi> had publiſhed that fatall Edict of the 16. of <hi>March</hi> 1629. touching the reſtitution of the poſſeſsions belonging to the Church, and bitterly execute it againſt ſo many ſupplications, appeales and proteſtations of the States: The Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> (as chiefe of the Proteſtants) ſummoned all the States,<note place="margin">The Dyet of <hi>Lipſich</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>March.</hi> 1623.</note> addicted to the <hi>Lutheran</hi> faith, to the Dyet of <hi>Lipſich:</hi> and declared unto them how the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Germany</hi> was oppreſſed, and the Princes of the Empire robbed of their rights and dignities, and incited them to the gathering up of Souldiers through all precincts, and to the arming of the Countrey people. Shortly after, as one that would by his owne Example leade the way to the reſt; hee levied an armie of 20000. men: and did in the name of himſelfe and of the Proteſtants make knowne to the Emperour, that unleſſe the grievances, exactions and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions laid upon the people by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18364:47"/> and the Souldiers, were forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with taken away, hee and his Allies would with armed power reſiſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſuch hainous and continuall inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. So the Proteſtants being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to rebellion, when <hi>Tilly</hi> did invade his territories with hoſtile cruelties, hee tooke up armes againſt the Emperour and his Leaguers: and by the valour of the <hi>Swedes</hi> he overthrew the armie of them both, with a glorious Victory at <hi>Lipſich.</hi> And preſently upon,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1633</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1634</label> it drawing after him a Common Warre through the whole Empire; hee made himſelfe Maſter of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the greater part of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and all <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he did alſo with perſwaſions and threatnings,<note place="margin">5. <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1634.</note> involve in the publike trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the States of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> who had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to beene of neither ſide.<note place="margin">In the moneths of <hi>February</hi> and <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1633.</note> And in the Convention of <hi>Hailbrun</hi> &amp; <hi>Frankford,</hi> exhorted all the Proteſtants to a firme concord and continuance of a Warre of Allies and Confederates. Yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18364:48"/> after that by the overthrow at <hi>Nordlingen,</hi> the forces of the Proteſtants being by little and little enfeebled, and thoſe of the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> by degrees increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1634</label> made the fortune of the War ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what doubtfull; hee putting off as it were, all faith together with the fortune of his Confederates: particular Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which hee had ſo often refuſed) being offered unto him, made his peace with the Emperor, clapt up a ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition for his owne ſafety to the great prejudice of his Confederates; and to the end, that hee alone might deſerue pardon and favour, excluded the moſt of the Vnited from pardon and <hi>Amne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia.</hi> And ſo, to the end, that he might free himſelfe from uncertaine dangers, he involved his confederates in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine deſtruction; and that hee might turne away from himſelfe, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of rebellion and treaſon; he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up his friends and Allies to bee puniſhed at the pleaſure of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. With a treachery ſo much the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18364:48"/> more odious, in that hee turned his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile armes againſt thoſe whom hee had not onely incited, but in a manner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to take armes againſt his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.<note place="margin">Dat veniam corvis vexat cenſura Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbas.</note> Therefore by what Iuſtice can a common crime be pardoned to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that it may bee puniſhed in the abbettors? By what equitie is a publike rebellion commended in the kindlers of it, that it may be puniſhed in the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers? Why are not all the Proteſtants being partners in one and the ſame miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; recompenſed with the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or chaſtiſed with the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. Why doth the ſame crime ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſome unto new honors and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, &amp; ſtrip others out of the dignities of their Anceſtors, and the habitations of of their Predeceſſors? Why is the head of treaſon adorned not with Laurell wreathes onely, but with Elegies or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonialls of honour? and the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which have unhappily joyned themſelves to him, boaſting himſelfe both in the Iuſtneſſe of their cauſe and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18364:49"/> ſtrength of armes, cut off from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as rotten limbes? Let ſuch changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fickle friends take heed, leaſt ſhortly in their turne they have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in themſelves of the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which they have approoved in their Confederates: and leaſt they in ſucceeding times doe to their owne da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, pay dearely for thoſe things which they ſuffer to be puniſhed as crimes, in their Confederates.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Becauſe they are not forced to a peace, but to a new Warre.</note>For it doth not neceſſarily follow, that if equall pardon, and common libertie doe ſeeme to have beene granted to ſome of the Proteſtants, by the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Prague;</hi> they doe preſently enjoy a comfortable peace, and a full tranquilitie and quiet of their territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Nay rather theſe enticements of Peace, are incitements to a more cruell Warre: that pleaſing name of pardon, is an oath to engage Souldiers, neither can any man make uſe of this pacification, but he muſt at the ſame ſame inſtant lead on bloudy armes: not againſt ſtrangers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18364:49"/> alone, but againſt his owne Allies and Patrones. To the end that Warre may be rooted out of the Countrey, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are entred into their pay, under new lawes: To the end that Peace may bee reſtored to the Empire a moſt blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Warre is denounced againſt many States of the Empire; which made the condition of all the Princes, ſo much the Worſe, that they doe not as free States and Common-wealths, make a Warre upon the common Enemies, at their owne will and pleaſure as heretofore they have done, on the behalfe of the Common-wealth for the Libertie of their owne Countrey, and for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and private Eſtates; but are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther compelled as hired ſervants and ſlaves deſtinated to ſlaughter, to beare armes againſt their Allies, fellow Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens and defenders; to waſte their ſtrength and ſubſtance with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary contributions, and to lend their owne bloud to the ſupporting of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Soveraigntie; with moſt ſevere
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18364:50"/> puniſhments adjudged againſt thoſe, who have beene or ſhould bee found negligent in gathering in the Souldiers pay in ſupplying them with proviſions, or in polling and vexing the Subjects e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven farre beneath the value of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. So that the Warre was not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, nor the exaction taken away, nor depopulations prohibited; but on the contrary, the Warre being before particular, is made generall; the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions which were extraordinary, are made ordinary; and the oppreſsions of Cities and Countries are carried on un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of military Iuſtice: and as all things decline towards the worſt, are like to goe on in a more rigorous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hereafter. Let us interrogate the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of former times, and to the end that we may know things to come, let us runne over thoſe that are paſt; and (which is the moſt certaine way of conjecture) let us call to mind things done, and compare them with things to bee done. For if the Emperour hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18364:50"/> in his owne Hereditarie Countries un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done ſome Citizens with feeding 20. or 30. ſouldiers in a day a piece: if he hath taxed his owne Subjects at a high daily rate towards the payments of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; if he doe continually lay new bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens upon his <hi>Hungarians,</hi> beſides the old pay, tributes, and taxations: What can wee hope will become of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, who having beene lately ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and now friends; rather out of neceſsitie then any will of their owne, have embraced a Peace, ſafe for their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, but diſgracefull to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Certainely as long as proviſion of corne ſhall be hard to be gotten (and ſo it will be, as long as an Armie of 80. Regiments, ſuch a one as all <hi>Europe</hi> never ſet forth againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> ſhall range up and downe <hi>Germany</hi>) the higheſt and loweſt will be oppreſſed with exceſſive pilling and ranſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they will bee compelled to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and feed at their owne charge, Souldiers armed at their charge; and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18364:51"/> both Horſe-boyes and Horſes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their carriages, that were bought with their money; and will be in the end, conſumed with the rapines, fire and ſword, of thoſe Souldiers upon whom they have beſtowed infinite favours. The free Cities of the Empire (as hath beene often done) will be compelled to feed, cheriſh, and recover, the all-moſt famiſhed armies, the povertie-peined Regiments, and diſperſed troupes; and to doe all that is to be done, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and piece them together, even to the new arming of them. And to the end, that they may defend themſelves from thoſe moſt rigorous exactions, povertie ſhall be deſired by them as a happineſſe; and that they may avoyd the Executioner, they will deſire to fall into the hands of him that is to begge or compound for their confiſcate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. And in vaine alleadging their rights and immunities before an Army that carries all before it; they ſhall heare that moſt inſolent ſpeech of <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:18364:51"/> to them of <hi>Meſsina</hi> when they made the like excuſe:<note place="margin">Plutarchus in Pompeio.</note> 
               <hi>Will you not ceaſe to tell us that are girt with ſwords, of your lawes and Priviledges?</hi> For certainely whileſt <hi>Mars</hi> is in his fury, lawes are ſilent; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie is a perpetuall patronage to an enormous power; neither are the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers pillages practiſed under any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther title, then that of common indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency. Violence defends whatſoever it hath compelled unto, and by a pretext of neceſſitie: of things unlawfull and ſhamefull, make things lawfull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. But that which is the moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing of all, the unhappieſt men will not dare to complaine of their cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: miſerable men will be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to ſhew their condition; the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed will bee compelled to faine themſelves happy: and when as in the moſt ſecret part of their houſe they ſhall by ſtealing a teare, diſcloſe their griefe to their wives and children, they ſhall appeare in publike with the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of another fortune. It will be a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18364:52"/> crime ſo much as to make a ſhew of ſadneſſe in their faſhion or carriage, to give eaſe to their hearts with juſtly deſerved ſighes, and to be more willing to ſeeme miſerable, then to bee ſo. It will be judged a great favour for a man to grant life to them he hath brought to povertie; to leave a ſonne to him, whoſe brother or wife hee hath ſlaine; and when hee hath robbed men of halfe their goods, to vouchſafe to reſtore him a third part: Neither will it bee lawfull for them to lament the loſſe of the moſt part of their eſtate, for feare leaſt all they have ſhould bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them. For where ſhall poore ſoules ſue for Iuſtice from their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours? Where ſhall they complaine of injuries, offered them? By what law ſhall they recover their goods taken from them?</p>
            <p>When as the whole Common-wealth being in diſorder, the Emperour alone ſhall compell the reſt of the Princes, being daunted with feare, to bee obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18364:52"/> to his ambition; when as the Iudgement of the Imperiall Chamber being neglected, all lawes ſhall bee at his pleaſure alone; and finally, when the equitie of the States being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and the libertie of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> taken away; the power of life and and death of all afflicted perſons ſhall be onely in his power.<note place="margin">3. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> not Hereditary.</note> Let the ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time moſt flouriſhing Kingdome of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and now the publike Theatre of the miſeries of the world, ſtand for an example; the State whereof, when as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other rights they had preſerved unto themſelves the intire libertie of Electing a King, and had maintained it both by word and deed, againſt <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand II.</hi> he being inſtantly growne the ſtronger in armes; of a partie became a judge, and decided that domeſticall controverſie by his owne private arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement; and did put to moſt cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures all thoſe, that did moove againſt him the controverſie, touching the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditarie ſucceſſion: And ſoone after to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18364:53"/> the end, that he might eſtabliſh that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall act by a generall ordinance; hee publikely declared, that the Kingdome was not wonne by valour; but due to him by ſucceſſion: When as neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Cuſtomes of all ages, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of many Emperours and Popes; and the Coronations of all their Kings, doe manifeſtly proove, that the <hi>Bohemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> have hitherto had free ſuffrages in the Election of their Princes.<note place="margin">Ioan. Dubra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Epiſc. Olomucenſis. Wenceſlaus Hagecius. Coſmas &amp; Pulcava in Hiſtoriis Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia. <hi>1197. 1212.</hi>
               </note> For, that we may ſeeke no further, when as <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſlaus</hi> in the yeare 1197. was crowned King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> at <hi>Mentz,</hi> by <hi>Phillip</hi> the Emperour; the Emperour <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, II.</hi> did by three ſeverall Letters Patents of the yeares 1212. 1216. and 1231. confirme the Election; and did by a ſacred reſcript declare, by what title, and in what manner the Kings of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> ſhould for the time to come obtaine the Kingdome, in theſe words: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring our pleaſure to bee, that whoſoever ſhall be choſen King by the Bohemians, doe repaire to us and our Succeſſours to receive
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18364:53"/> his Royall ornaments after the due manner.</hi> And the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth did ſo openly confirme this ſuffrage of free Election in the Dyet of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire held at <hi>Norimberg</hi> in the yeare 1356.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1356</label> that when as he had determined by the golden Bull then publiſhed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. that all the ſecular Electorſhips ſhould by lawfull ſucceſſion bee devolved to their Heires; yet he did particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> as an Elective Electorſhip in theſe words: <hi>Saving ever the priviledges, rights, and cuſtomes of our Kingdome of Bohemia, upon an Election to be made of their King in caſe of vacancie, by the Inhabitants of the Kingdome, who have the right of chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the King of Bohemia, according as it is contained in their priviledges; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their continually oſberved Cuſtome: which wee doe decree, that it ſhall now, and in all future times, hold his undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted force and vigour in the whole tenor and forme thereof.</hi> Neither ought the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate declaration of the ſame Emperour
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18364:54"/> 
               <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth, made in favour of the Houſe of <hi>Lutzembourgh,</hi> to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt the publike conſtitution of the Dyet: both becauſe it was made without the conſent of the States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in the yeare 1348.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1348</label> by <hi>Charles,</hi> before hee was Emperour, and when he had not ſo much reſpect to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as to his owne domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Intereſts: and alſo becauſe all the ſucceeding Kings of what Family ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, did by their reverſall Letters, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after the uſuall <hi>Bohemian</hi> cuſtome, ſolemnely profeſſe, that they attained the Regall Dignitie by the Decree, and free Election of the States. Even <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the Firſt, although hee were the ſonne in law of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; and brother in law to <hi>Lewis</hi> his predeceſſor; and grounded his title up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the publike diſpoſition of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law by will of the Hereditarie ſucceſſion of <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife, in the yeare 1510.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1510</label> Yet in a ſolemne recognition made before the States in the yeare 1526.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1526</label>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:18364:54"/> he freely proteſted: <hi>That the Barons, Nobles, Cities, and the whole Commonaltie of the Kingdome of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>did of their free and good will, according to the liberties of the Kingdome chooſe him King of</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, <hi>not of any due, &amp;c.</hi> And although he being afterwards induced to it by the Counſels of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the yeare 1545.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1545</label> did indeavour to overthrow that recognition, under a pretence of errour found in it; yet hee being ſoone taught by experience that unto a Nation moſt covetous of libertie, it was a thing more pleaſing that Kings ſhould bee given, then borne; in an Aſſembly which hee called at <hi>Prague,</hi> in the yeare 1549.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1549</label> hee did moſt graciouſly intreat the States, and moſt freely obtained of them; that his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Maximilian</hi> might bee deſigned King by them. And <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> againe in the yeare 1575.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1575</label> with much intreaty and inſtat ſuite, obtained of the States of the Kingdome, that his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Rodulph</hi> might onely upon ſome certaine conditions ſucceed him in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18364:55"/> Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> And hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by a Tranſ-action at <hi>Prague,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in an Aſſembly there, in the yeare 1608.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1608</label> yielded up the Kingdome to his Brother <hi>Matthias I.</hi> upon condition, that the States of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces, ſhould approove this reſignation: yea, even <hi>Ferdinand II.</hi> himſelfe in the yeare 1617.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1617</label> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> in an Aſſembly at <hi>Prague</hi> unto the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Kingdome; and by their conſent crowned King of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (as their manner is) his reverſall letters, did amply commend that free Election. What was it needfull for him to deſire more, if the Kingdome were due unto him by right of birth? What reaſon was there for him to gaine thoſe things by ſuite, and labouring for voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the right of his owne birth and title of lawfull ſucceſsion freely gave him? Beſides, why hath there beene none of thoſe Kings children hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto found, who after the uſuall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18364:55"/> of Hereditarie States, would either call himſelfe Prince of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or ſuffer himſelfe to bee ſo called by his father? Why did ſo many forreigne Princes at ſuch times as the government of the Kingdome was often vacant, ſend Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, labouring, promiſing, and offring of gifts ſue, that in that Election conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration might bee had of them and theirs? as it appeareth in hiſtories that the Emperour <hi>Albert</hi> did for his ſonne <hi>Frederick,</hi> in the yeare 1307. the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Henry VII.</hi> for his brother <hi>Walram,</hi> in the yeare 1610. The Emperour <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmund IV.</hi> for his ſonne in law <hi>Albert</hi> in the yeare 1437. to omit many others: Who, if they had believed that the Kings of <hi>Bohemia</hi> were made by ſucceſsion, would never in ſuch an abundance of bloud-Royall, in the ſight of the whole World have lien in waite for another mans inheritance againſt all right and juſtice. Why was the Scepter by the moſt free ſuffrages of the States, often tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18364:56"/> to other families, although there were many Heires left alive of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent? as was done both in the yeare 1306. when <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the Third, being ſlaine; and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Carinthia</hi> his ſonne in law who was a Competitor, being put by, <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Firſt, ſonne of <hi>Albert</hi> the Emperour, was choſen; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Barons of <hi>Suihoven</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemburgh,</hi> deſcended of the Heires male in a right line, were ready to have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded; and alſo in the yeare 1458. when <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> being dead, <hi>George Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicbradius</hi> having no manner of affinitie with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> or <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> being freely choſen by the States was confined by the Bulls of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Second, and by the reſcripts of <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> the Emperour,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1459</label> in the yeare 1459. although <hi>Caſimire</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Saxony,</hi> whereof the one had married the younger, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the elder ſiſter of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> did with moſt earneſt ſolicitation labour for the Kingdome. Why did the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18364:56"/> Princes often obtaine peaceable poſſeſsion of the Kingdome, when the brethren and eldeſt ſonnes were put by it? as when in the yeare 1324.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1324</label> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Carinthia</hi> who had married <hi>Anne</hi> the elder daughter of <hi>Wenceſlaus VI.</hi> being rejected, <hi>Iohn I.</hi> ſonne to the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, founder of the family of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the younger, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and accepted for King by the States. For by the law of nature, and lawfull cuſtome of ſucceſsion, males are preferred before females, and the elder of the ſame ſex, before the younger. But I forbeare to hold a candle to the Sunne at noone-day, ſince his Imperiall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie would have this cauſe, to be decided not by reaſons, but by armes; and doth found his principall title to the Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary poſſeſsion of the Kingdome,<note place="margin">Ius heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium in regno Bohemiae Ferdinandi II. editum Viennae. <hi>1620</hi> in <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> rather upon the recovery or conqueſt thereof, then upon their acceptance; having in the beginning of the booke that is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed touching his Hereditarie right to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18364:57"/> the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> clearely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. <hi>That although his Hereditarie right were doubtfull, and the</hi> Bohemians <hi>have hitherto had ſome right of free Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet now, ſince the whole Kingdome is come to him by force of armes, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him for their lawfull Heire all of due, not at their pleaſure; it is in vaine to hold any further diſpute touching the right of Election; ſince the Kingdome it ſelfe being reduced under his power, did now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the hereditary right of the Houſe of Auſtria thereunto.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Innocent <hi>Sileſia</hi> is ſtripped of her rights.</note> I come now to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia,</hi> and the united Provinces of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia:</hi> who, where as heretofore, for the defence of their rights and liberties, they did unite themſelves to that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; are at this day by this tranſ-acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Prague;</hi> not onely deprived of all rights and immunities, but alſo by He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary right, made ſubject to a forrein power. The unjuſtneſſe of which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, that it may bee prooved from the very originall of the matter it ſelfe; it is to be conſidered that the Province of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18364:57"/> 
               <hi>Sileſia</hi> was anciently ſubject unto <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioach. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Sileſiae. editis. Witte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergae. <hi>1571.</hi>
               </note> and divided by divers Dutchies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Princes of the <hi>Sarmatian</hi> bloud: Afterwards in ſucceeding times they diſdained the pride of the <hi>Sarmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> after experience had of the faithfull and friendly offices of the <hi>Bohemians</hi> in many of their affaires, of their owne free will and voluntary inclination, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Imperious command of the <hi>Polonians,</hi> in the yeare 1331.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1331</label> they ſued for the protection of <hi>Iohn I.</hi> King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia:</hi> and for this cauſe, <hi>Sileſia</hi> being aſſaulted by the <hi>Polonians</hi> with a moſt grievous warre,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1337</label> and valiantly defended by the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> did deliver it ſelfe up wholly into the patronage and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> vpon this covenant and condition; that all their rights, liberties, and priviledges, ſhould be preſerved ſafe and entire. Whereof amongſt others, one notable teſtimonie hath remained untill our times, that the States of that Province doe not ſweare alleagiance unto the King elected, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18364:58"/> till hee have bound himſelfe unto them by giving a caution for the ratifying, and maintaining of their lands, rights, and honours; and by the confirmation of them by the ſignature of his Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall letters, and by a ſolemne oath. And according to this agreement, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charles IV.</hi> by a ſpeciall Charter given at <hi>Prague,</hi> the ſeventh of the Ides of <hi>October,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1355</label> in the yeare 1355. did for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unite, incorporate, and inſeparably ly annex that whole Country with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> and <hi>Luſatia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Both theſe are extant in the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of <hi>Goldaſtus, Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 345. 1356.</note> unto the Scepter of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> which Incorporation the Princes of the Empire did afterwards approove, at the Dyet held at <hi>Norim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> in the yeare 1356. and did alſo confirme it by the Reſcript or Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Gerlac</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and Lord High Chancellor of the ſacred <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. And in purſuance of this right, the <hi>Sileſians</hi> have ever ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> that they did not onely give their free voice at their Election; but alſo at their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18364:58"/> obtained moſt ample Reverſall letters; which it appeareth that even the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Kings themſelves did moſt freely grant; namely, <hi>Ferdinand I.</hi> the fourteenth of <hi>Ianuary</hi> in the yeare 1527.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1527</label> 
               <hi>Maximilian II.</hi> in the yeare 1557. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulph II.</hi> in the yeares 1577. and 1609. and even <hi>Ferdinand II.</hi> in the yeare 1617. Nay further,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1617</label> when the laſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles aroſe in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Sileſians</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the <hi>Bohemians</hi> their Confederates, and they were over throwne in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Prague;</hi> yet the <hi>Sileſians</hi> would not lay downe their armes untill <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> the Second at a ſolemne Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action made at <hi>Preſlaw</hi> the one and twentieth of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the yeare 1621.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1621</label> religiouſly promiſed the States, that if they would renounce the Election of the Prince <hi>Palatine Fredericke,</hi> hee would preſerve all their rights and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges unviolated; which promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confirmed by oath, and a ſacred Charter; the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> being then the Emperours Commiſſary, and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18364:59"/> for the States, did undertake by caution given, by himſelfe to ſee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>And although the States of <hi>Sileſia</hi> did forthwith abandon the Prince <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> Partie; yet nevertheleſſe, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour in the yeares 1628.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1628</label> and 1629. contrary to his covenants and promiſes, abrogated many of their rights and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> conniving thereunto. And the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> himſelfe, when as being provoked thereunto by the Emperours Edict, and unjuſt dealing; hee had ſtirred up gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all the armes of the Proteſtants throughout the Empire; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> and had in an hoſtile manner gotten poſſeſſion of the Kingdome and head Citie of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> did ſtirre up the Princes and States of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> (which till then had beene of neither ſide) not onely by letters ſigned with his owne hand the fifth of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1634.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1634</label> to revolt and to maintaine their priviledges as he called them; but alſo, ſending againſt them Generall <hi>Arnheim</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18364:59"/> with a huge Armie, compelled the Dukes and Cities which till then ſtood doubtfull; partly by threatnings, and partly by open force unto rebellion, and put <hi>Saxon</hi> Garriſons into the chiefe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Fortreſſes.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1635</label> And yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe afterwards, his purpoſes changing with the fortune, hee was the firſt that ſtarted from the Generall League; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to purchaſe his owne eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the ruine of his Allies; and ſuffered the moſt unfortunate States of <hi>Sileſia</hi> (who relying upon his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and aſſurance, and juſtice of the Common cauſe, did not at the firſt take armes, but joyned their armes to the <hi>Saxons</hi>) ſhamefully to be excluded out of the <hi>Amneſtia;</hi> being innocent, and deſerving no ill, and delivered them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be puniſhed at the Emperours ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute will and pleaſure; and did by his anſwer given the fifteenth day of <hi>Iune,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1635</label> with cold comfort ſend away their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and Embaſſadors (craving per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of publike faith) to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18364:60"/> to begge his pardon. And ſo having deſerved ſingular well of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> he expiated the crime of his owne rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, with the puniſhment of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent friends: and not content to have waſted the moſt noble Province of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> with Warre and rapines; he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the innocent Inhabitants, and ſuch as had not beene offendors, but by his inſtigation, to the pleaſure of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And for a reward of this his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervice done to the Empire, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his egregious treacherie, hee hath upper and nether <hi>Luſatia</hi> beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1621</label> which being heretofore againſt all right and juſtice, hewen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the roote of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had ingaged unto him by way of morgage, for the charge of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> warre. In the collation of which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, the unjuſtice of both ſeemeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall; as well of the Emperour in being profuſe of another mans eſtate; as of the <hi>Saxon</hi> in making an unlawfull purchaſe. For to repeate ſhortly the originall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18364:60"/> touching this Province alſo; when as <hi>Luſatia</hi> in the yeare 1075.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1075</label> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſtowed by the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, upon <hi>Vratiſlaus</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> together with the Crowne, for a reward of his valour, was ſhortly after aſsigned by <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> with the one eie, in the yeare 1191.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1191</label> to <hi>Otto</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> as a dowrie with his Daughter <hi>Beatrice:</hi> After the death of the Marqueſſe <hi>Walderam</hi> (who died without iſſue) in the yeare 1312.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1312</label> at the requeſt of the Inhabitants, it was reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe by <hi>Iohn</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in the yeare 1319.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1319</label> and by the Charter of the Emperour, <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourth, in the yeare 1328.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1328</label> was inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably united to the Crowne: Which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, did afterwards by a publike Edict confirmed in the Dyet of <hi>Norimbergh,</hi> in the yeare 1356.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1356</label> to ſettle and eſtabliſh, that this Province being for ever appropriated, indiviſibly annexed, and inſeperably added to <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia;</hi> could never be transferred to a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18364:61"/> government, without the aſſent of the States themſelves. Therefore <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the Eighth,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1411</label> in the yeare 1411. and ſhortly after, his brother <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour, in the yeare 1414. being intreated thereunto by the foure States of the Province; did by ſpeciall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Cautions for ever provide, that it ſhould never after by any title, be alienated from the Kingdome of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia.</hi> Which right and priviledge the Inhabitants themſelves have beene ſo carefull to maintaine; that when as King <hi>Laudiſlaus</hi> Nephew to <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> had ſold the ſame for a valuable price to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh:</hi> when hee was dead, <hi>George</hi> his ſucceſſor being mooved with the mony and ſuite of the Subjects; did in the yeare 1470.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1470</label> reſtore it to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: this being eſtabliſhed as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable law, that it ſhould never after by any pretext whatſoever, be alienated from the very bowells of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And yet in our age <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18364:61"/> the Second,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1620</label> that after he had taken away the generall harmonie and Concord of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> together with their rights: when hee had cut the ſinewes of the body, hee tore in pieces the feeble members, he purchaſed the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Lawes and Immunities of the whole Kingdome; by the diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Provinces anciently united to it. And as one not ſo much liberall of another mans eſtate, as prodigall of that which was none of his owne; he ſold a portion of the Elective Kingdome, that hee might make the whole, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary to him and his.</p>
            <p>But to come to that which is the chiefe point of the whole buſineſſe.<note place="margin">6. The Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dignity unjuſtly conferred upon the <hi>Bavarian.</hi>
               </note> At this conſpiracie of <hi>Prague,</hi> the chiefe of the ſecular Elector-Princes; and the Prime member of the Empire next unto the Emperour; being not ſo much as called: unheard, unconvicted, is ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of his Hereditary rights; and his Territories and Dignities are diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18364:62"/> the ſervice they had done to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour againſt him; and that expreſſely contrary to the fundamentall lawes of the golden Bull Chap. 3. and againſt the Emperours owne Capitulation, in the 36. Article, which ordaines, <hi>That the principall member of the Empire, and the baſes and pillars thereof, the Electors; and eſpecially the ſeculars, ſhould remaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken.</hi> Neither is there any other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour given for that, unheard of proſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; then the unhappineſſe of the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian</hi> Warre: In which, when the Prince Elector <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Fifth, had engaged himſelfe as in a particular qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, betwixt the States of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and their King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second. <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> in the meane time, his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune favouring him, being advanced to the Empire; out of a private cauſe, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a publike crime; and ſo farre tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all the actions of the Prince <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> undertaken againſt him as King of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> as to bring them within compaſſe of treaſon againſt his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18364:62"/> Majeſtie; when as hee had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted no offence at all, neither againſt the Empire, nor Emperour: nay, on the contrary in the Aſſembly of <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1620</label> had aſſiſted <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second with his voyce; and did deſire that the Controverſie, touching the Scepter of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> might bee decided by an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary tryall, all hoſtility laid aſide. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> being growne the ſtronger not in right, but in power; and having overthrowne the <hi>Bohemians</hi> at the White Hill, commonly called <hi>Weiſſemberge:</hi> did not onely proſcribe the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> unheard, and his cauſe never underſtood: but alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving divided the <hi>Palatinate</hi> betwixt the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards;</hi> did upon his owne private pleaſure, the States of the Empire being never conſulted with; grant unto <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> the Electorall Dignitie, which hee had promiſed unto him, upon a league made betwixt them at <hi>Munchen,</hi> long before the <hi>Bohemian</hi> troubles: and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18364:63"/> through private and domeſticall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1619.</hi> Henricus Stero Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſis in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalibus, A. <hi>300.</hi> Aventinus lib. <hi>7.</hi> Annal. Boior. p. <hi>587.</hi>
               </note> deprived him of all his rights and Territories; unto whom of ancient right it belonged to take cogniſance of cauſes mooved to the King or Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the <hi>Romans.</hi> As if the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Emperour could by any right transferre the moſt noble Fees and Seignories of the Empire, according to his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate fancie; and beſtow them upon ſuch as have deſerved well of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> meerely at his owne pleaſure: who, as it appeareth by the 28. Article of the golden Bull, cannot diſpoſe ſo much as of a County, or any other eſtate or fortune being devolved to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, without the conſent of the States of the Empire. The Electorſhips, Dutchies, and Counties, be Fees of the Empire, not of the <hi>Emperour;</hi> but as hee is the Head, Miniſter, and Vicar of the Empire: and therefore he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Oath of Alleagiance of the Princes in the name of himſelfe, but of the Empire. And at the breaking up of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18364:63"/> the Dyet of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> in the yeare 1555.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1555</label> it was ordained; that the Controverſies which aroſe betwixt the States of the Empire, touching the Imperiall Fees and Seignories, ſhould not bee decided, but in the generall Aſſembly of the States. And for this cauſe <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King of <hi>France,</hi> in the yeare 1551.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1551</label> did by his Embaſſador juſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, before the States of the Empire; that <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, his cauſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard, and his right neglected; had beſtowed upon his ſonne <hi>Philip</hi> the Dutchie of <hi>Milan</hi> and Vicarage of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ena,</hi> without their conſent, or approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the <hi>Emperour Rodulph II.</hi> in the yeare 1598.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1598</label> did moſt Heroically an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Admirall demanding the Vicountie of <hi>Beſanzon</hi> in the name of the King his Maſter, <hi>That the Fees of the Empire could bee taken away from no man, nor be transferred upon any other, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the Electors and States.</hi> Certainely, according to the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the feudall lawes, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18364:64"/> concerning Fees ought to bee determined by the Iudgement of the Peeres. <hi>And if a queſtion doe ariſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Lord and his Vaſſals concerning any matter of Fee, it muſt be decided by the Peeres of the Court,</hi> lib. 1. de feud. tit. x. ſec. 1. <hi>And they ought to determine Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies touching benefices, who doe hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices of the ſame Lord,</hi> lib. 1. tit. 26. And although the <hi>Emperour</hi> did deſire to have ſuch an apparant injurie approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the States of the Empire,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1623</label> in the Dyet held at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> yet the Electors of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and many other Princes of the Empire did by their Embaſſadors make proteſtation, and alleadge; <hi>That the Tranſlation of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall dignitie upon the Duke of</hi> Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, <hi>was contrary to the Conſtitutions of the golden Bull, to the fundamentall lawes of the Empire, to the declaration of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> Sigiſmund <hi>the Fourth, to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of feudall right; and in a word, to the accords and covenants agreed upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Houſes of the Prince</hi> Palatine,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18364:64"/> 
               <hi>and</hi> Bavaria, <hi>long ſince eſtabliſhed, by the providence of their fore-fathers; and ſtrengthned with the proſcription of almoſt</hi> 300. <hi>yeares: That the Prince</hi> Palatine <hi>was condemned, being never ſummoned, never heard, and his cauſe never opened: When as hee nevertheleſſe was not the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the</hi> Bohemian <hi>troubles; and many that were partners in the ſame crime, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pardon of the Emperour; and that therefore they could not conſent to ſuch a precipitate proſcription, and ſtripping him out of his Eſtate.</hi> And therefore alſo, when as the Emperour rejecting all theſe exceptions, oppoſitions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of the States, beſtowed the Fee of the Electorate upon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria:</hi> the Embaſſadours of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> refuſed to be preſent at the ceremonies of his Inveſture; leaſt by their preſence they ſhould ſeeme to have approoved ſo enormous an act of injuſtice. And a little after, the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors did by their letters ſent to the Emperour from <hi>Amburgh;</hi> complaine
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18364:65"/> of the violation of the right of their Colledge of Electors; and by a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like inſtrument under their owne hands, did confirme and make good all that had beene ſaid and done by their Embaſſadors. And although the yeare following, the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> being drawne on by the cunning of <hi>Ludovike</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Darmſtadt,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1624</label> did at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of <hi>Schleufingen</hi> receive the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> into the Septemvirall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for a time; perſwading himſelfe, that that Colledge being made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate, an univerſall Peace would be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the <hi>Empire.</hi> Yet that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion being made upon certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; he proteſted, hee intended not that any thing done ſhould prejudice the rights of the Houſe of the Prince <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> nor the proteſtations exhibited by his Embaſſadors at <hi>Ratisbone:</hi> Which afterwards both in the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Mulhauſen,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1627. 1630.</label> and at the Diet of <hi>Ratisbone;</hi> and in ſeverall Declarations and reſolutions, ſent unto divers Princes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18364:65"/> of <hi>Europe;</hi> and even in that league made at <hi>Torgaw,</hi> in the yeare 1631.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> with the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh;</hi> he did ever conſtantly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and affirme: having proteſted in all places, and before all men; that no Peace was ever to bee hoped for in the Empire, without reſtitution of the Houſe of the Prince <hi>Palatine.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with what conſcience dareth hee at this day publiſh that Tranſ-action to have beene juſt, ſacred, and moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the <hi>Empire:</hi> Whereby, it is not onely certaine, that the equalitie of voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being taken away amongſt the ſeven Electors, the Proteſtants will ever goe downe the winde; but alſo, ſo long as there ſhall be one drop remaining of the <hi>Palatine</hi> bloud, from which this digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie if not regall; yet certainely next to it, is ſo violently taken away againſt all right and Iuſtice; it is manifeſt, that <hi>Germany</hi> will bee perpetually infeſted, with new troubles. For be it admitted, not granted, that the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18364:66"/> hath by ſuch heinous crimes deſerved proſcription, and ſtripping out of his Patrimony: By what law or right, are his children, brother, and all his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, as innocent and giltleſſe as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though differing in cauſe, involved nevertheleſſe in the ſame puniſhment: When as both his ſonnes before their Fathers offence had the Electorall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, belonging to them by right of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; and alſo by the Common law of Fees it is manifeſt, <hi>That the offence of one of the Heires of the Fee doth not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the reſt,</hi> lib. 2. de feud. t. 78. <hi>and yet the act of a brother doth not hurt his brother in his Hereditary Fee.</hi> tit. 93. <hi>Yea more, if a vaſſall ſhall commit ſo enormous a crime, that he or thoſe that deſcend of him, ought to be deprived of his inheritance; yet his kinsfolkes in the fourth degree are to be reſtored to the poſſeſsion thereof,</hi> lib. 2. tit. 26. And therefore very wiſely the Duke of <hi>Neuburgh</hi> being neerer of kinne to the Princes <hi>Palatine,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1623</label> then to the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> obtained of the Emperour rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18364:66"/> letters, whereby proviſion was made, that this Tranſ-action of Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Dignitie upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſhould at no time, nor in any ſort prejudice the right of himſelfe, or of his, founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a nearer degree of bloud.</p>
            <p>Neither doth this appeare to be a leſſe argument of ſo barbarous an injurie, that the whole <hi>Electorate</hi> being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon the <hi>Bavarian;</hi> yet the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories are divided amongſt divers Princes; and the upper <hi>Palatinate</hi> is aſſigned to the <hi>Bavarian,</hi> and the lower to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for the charge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of the <hi>German</hi> Warre. Whereas by the Conſtitution of the golden Bull, <hi>Chap.</hi> 25. (the title whereof is,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1356</label> Of the intireneſſe of the Principalities of the <hi>Electors) Thoſe Illuſtrious and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Principalities; that is to ſay, the Kingdome of Bohemia, the County Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of the Rheine, the Dutchy of Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Marquiſat of Brandenburgh, and their Lands, Territories, and all other things belonging to them, cannot, nor ought
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18364:67"/> upon any condition whatſoever, be cut in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, divided, or diſmembred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. The <hi>Bavari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently no right to the Electorſhip.</note>The <hi>Bavarians</hi> perceiving the cauſe of tranſlation to bee entangled with theſe difficulties; and having many ages ſince ſought for ſome pretext for their ambition, doe deviſe moſt ancient titles for their new uſurpation; and doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Electorall dignitie was not ſo much conferred upon them by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">Gewoldus de S. R. Imperii Septemuira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis <hi>c. x.</hi> Fabius Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynianus Cancellariae Anhaltinae. P. <hi>11.</hi> p. <hi>83. 1215.</hi>
               </note> of his grace and favour to them, as recovered for their due by force of armes; and if it being moſt unjuſtly taken away from the Houſe of <hi>Bavaria</hi> by <hi>Charles IV,</hi> in the yeare 1354. was in reſpect of affinitie tranſlated to the Family of the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Rhyne:</hi> And that therefore the Princes <hi>Palatine</hi> unjuſtly; but the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> moſt juſtly did complaine of the alienation of the Electorall right; and that they may therefore lawfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence their ſuite for the recovery of the profits thereof, which have beene enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ever ſince <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourths time.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18364:67"/> Therefore to the end, that the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this Impoſture may bee made manifeſt to all men; it will be neceſſary to open the ſtate of the whole matter from the beginning. Ever ſince the firſt inſtitution of the Electors; the right of electing the <hi>Emperour</hi> hath beene in the power of the Counts <hi>Palatine,</hi> which were alſo Dukes of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the ancient Hiſtories of thoſe times. And in the yeare 1215.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1215</label> by the mariage of <hi>Otho</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> with <hi>Agnes,</hi> daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the laſt Count <hi>Palatine;</hi> the <hi>Palatinate</hi> of <hi>Rhine</hi> was united with the Dukedome of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Otho</hi> himſelfe the firſt of the Family of the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> in the right devolved unto him by his wife, became Elector: So the dignitie united with the Seigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1295</label> remained in the Houſe of <hi>Bavaria</hi> untill the yeare 1295. At which time <hi>Lodovike</hi> the Third being dead, his ſonnes divided his inheritance in this manner: that <hi>Rodulph</hi> his eldeſt ſhould hold the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> with the right of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18364:68"/> Electorall power; and <hi>Lodovike</hi> the younger, the upper <hi>Bavaria;</hi> and after his brothers death, hee ſhould hold the power of Election for terme of his life; as appeareth by the Tranſ-action made betwixt them at <hi>Munchen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1313.</hi> Extat apud Gewoldum de S.R. Imp. Septemvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratu. p. <hi>224. 1314.</hi>
               </note> in the yeare 1313. But <hi>Lodovicke</hi> the younger, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the fortune of the Warres; whileſt he bore armes againſt the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians,</hi> in the yeare 1314. was declared <hi>Emperour</hi> by the Major part of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors; his brother <hi>Rodulph</hi> and the Electors of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Collen,</hi> beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their voices upon <hi>Fredericke III.</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Whereupon grew a civill Warre in <hi>Germany; Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vike</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> being the ſtronger in armes, ſtripped his Brother <hi>Rodulph,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king part with his enemies, out of all his Territories; and having proſcribed him, forced him with his children to retire into <hi>England;</hi> where, a little while after,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1317</label> with griefe of heart he died. Yet ſoone after that, <hi>Fredericke</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> being taken priſoner and depoſed: <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovike</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18364:68"/> the Fourth, mooved with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration of his Brothers children, did by the Tranſ-action of <hi>Norimburgh,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1329</label> in the yeare 1329. reſtore to <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and <hi>Rupert,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Extat imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta apud Gewoldum. p. <hi>218.</hi>
               </note> ſonnes of his Brother <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Firſt, their Hereditary Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories and dignities, vpon this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that they yielding up the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Electorall right, ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Septemvirall Suffrage, with his ſonnes <hi>Lodovik</hi> and <hi>Stephan;</hi> and ſo both of them in their turnes ſhould E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the King of the <hi>Romans;</hi> which Tranſaction, though extorted from him by force, hee did yet cauſe to bee publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Dyet at <hi>Franckford,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1339</label> in the yeare 1339. But the <hi>Emperour Lodovike</hi> the Fourth, being excommunicate and dead; when <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> ſonne in law to <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Firſt; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1342</label> and Brother in law to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>Palatine</hi> Princes, came to ſway the Empire; <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Second, and <hi>Rupert</hi> the <hi>Palatine</hi> Princes; complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>Emperour</hi> their Kinſman by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18364:69"/> marriage, of violence and injurie offered them; and challenging the entire right of Election to belong unto them, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eldeſt ſonnes; did ſue to have the Tranſ-action of <hi>Norimburgh,</hi> touching the alternative Election betwixt the Houſe of the <hi>Palatines</hi> and <hi>Bavaria;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated, as being moſt unjuſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from them by force. So <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth favouring the moſt juſt cauſe, cauſed the buſineſſe to be brought into debate; and having obtained the conſent of all the Electors and States,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1354</label> in the yeare 1354. reſtored the Hereditary right of the entire Electorall Suffrage unto <hi>Rupert I.</hi> the <hi>Palatine</hi> Prince (for his elder Brother <hi>Rodulph</hi> a little before,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1356</label> in the yeare 1353. died) and excluding <hi>Lodovike</hi> and <hi>Stephan</hi> Dukes of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> publiſhed an ordinance touching the right and ſucceſsion of the Counts <hi>Palatine,</hi> in the voyce and election of the <hi>Roman Emperour;</hi> and cauſed it to bee ſent unto all the Electors. Yea, and about two yeares after, in the yeare
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18364:69"/> 1356. in a Diet held at <hi>Norimbergh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1356.</hi> Extat u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumque Mandatum &amp; Diploma apud Golda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum. Tom. <hi>4.</hi> Conſtit. Imper. p. <hi>345</hi>
               </note> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a publike Charter, confirming the ſame, to be approoved and ſigned by all the Electors. Which he the more eaſily effected; becauſe in the ſame Diet hee had conferred upon <hi>Lodovike</hi> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſonne to <hi>Lodovike</hi> the Fourth <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour;</hi> the Marquiſate and Electorate of <hi>Brandenburgh:</hi> as a recompence for the right of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Electorate.</p>
            <p>Whereby it appeareth, that it is a moſt falſe calumnie of them that affirme that the Counts <hi>Palatine</hi> did by the conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, take away from the <hi>Bavarian,</hi> the ancient right of voyce and Electorall dignitie. When as on the contrary, it is manifeſt out of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentike records, and all the Hiſtories of thoſe times; that the Princes <hi>Palatine</hi> did in no ſort invade any right of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans, and that was not due to themſelves: but did recover their Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarie rights which was extorted from them by <hi>Lodovike</hi> the Fourth, by force and fraud; and did unite it for ever to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18364:70"/> the Houſe of the <hi>Palatines</hi> of <hi>Rhyne;</hi> by the conſent of all the Electors and Princes of the Empire. And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that the <hi>Bavarians</hi> before their late intruſion, had never any right at all to the Electorate: nor were ever like to have, otherwiſe then by a violent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. For, let both the tranſlations be compared; that of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, upon the Prince <hi>Palatine Rupert:</hi> and of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, upon <hi>Maximilian</hi> of <hi>Bavaria:</hi> and the Iuſtice of the one, and the injuſtice of the other will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more cleare then the noone-day. In the one, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, did not ſo much out of grace beſtow the Electorall Dignitie upon <hi>Rupert</hi> the Prince <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> as of due reſtore it being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his Vncle by force. In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second, granted the Dignitie, being taken away from the Prince <hi>Palatine Fredericke</hi> the Fifth, without deſert, unto the <hi>Bavarian:</hi> who can pretend no right at all unto it. In the one, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth having formerly obtained the conſent of all the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18364:70"/> Electors, did in the publike Aſſembly of the Empire reſtore unto the Prince <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> the Suffrage of Election: even <hi>Lodovike</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> aſſenting thereunto. To whom it moſt properly belonged, to perpetuate ſo great an honour to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. In the other, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, upon the league made at <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen;</hi> for ſending of aide againſt the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> ſold the <hi>Palatinate</hi> to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian,</hi> before the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> had ſet a foot in <hi>Bohemia:</hi> and againſt the publike exceptions, oppoſitions, and appeales of all the Proteſtants, thruſt <hi>Maximilian</hi> into it by force. Laſtly, in the one, <hi>Lodovike</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Roman,</hi> ſonne to the Emperour <hi>Lodovike</hi> the Fourth, having received the Electorate of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> in the yeare 1352.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1352</label> upon the reſignation of his brother, <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vike</hi> the firſt: did by a ſolemne renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation yield up the right of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Electorate,</hi> to his Coſin Germane: In the other, the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> did
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18364:71"/> neither in his owne name, nor in the name of his Brother or Kinsfolkes ever renounce his ſo lawfull right: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe to undergoe all extremities, and even a ten yeares baniſhment; then he would ſuffer himſelfe to be ſo unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deprived of ſo illuſtrious a dignitie. For, as for that which by the Tranſ-acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Prague,</hi> is offered to the Princes <hi>Palatine;</hi> that if laying aſide the right of the Electorate, they will come like humble ſuppliants, and begge pardon of the <hi>Emperour:</hi> lands and revenues, competent for their family and deſcent, ſhould bee aſſigned unto them: it is much like to the pleaſant deviſe of the Triumvirie in <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour was granted unto him,<note place="margin">Dion Caſſius Hiſtor. lib. <hi>47.</hi> p. <hi>336</hi>
               </note> that ſhould willingly yield up the poſſeſſion of his whole eſtate; that he might afterwards be repoſſeſſed of a third part of it. And that was (ſaith the Hiſtorian) to receive juſt nothing at all; and beſides, to looſe all their labour and travaile. For they who were ſtripped by open violence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18364:71"/> of the whole two parts of their eſtate, how ſhould they receive a third part backe againe: eſpecially when their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates were ſold to the ſouldiers at ſo cheape rates? Beſides, this Injurie done to the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> threatneth the like to the reſt of the Princes: and the excluſion of the chiefe of the Princes, draweth with it the ruine of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour States. For if the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conquerours, bee not aſhamed to deale ſo ſhamefully with the Head of the Electors, what can wee hope will become of the reſt of the members of the Empire: who neither in power, nor dignitie, nor amitie of ſtrangers, are to be compared with him? Certainely, whoſoever of the Proteſtants ſhall apply themſelves to their partie: they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> be bereaved of their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, their fortreſſes, and their owne troupes: and being by that meanes made naked, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and diſarmed; ſhall onely beare the empty name of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18364:72"/> And whoſoever ſhall refuſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to yield his necke to the yoake which heretofore the <hi>Germans</hi> have bin unacquainted with; and ſhall not with cloſed eies accept of any Articles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: they ſhall forthwith, after the examples of the Dukes of <hi>Wirtembergh,</hi> be proſcribed as enemies of the Empire; and guilty of treaſon againſt his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſtie, and be ſtripped of all their Patrimonies. The Imperiall Cities, which were anciently free after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Donawert, Ratisbone,</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurgh,</hi> ſhall bee delivered up to their Allies for the expences of the Warre: and under the name of being mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, ſhall bee inſlaved in perpetuall ſervitude to uſurping Lords. But for <hi>Germany,</hi> enough; and perhaps more then was fit, hath beene ſaid of it. I would to God there had not been more and more odious things done, then hath beene ſaid: and that worſe miſchiefes were not to be feared, then are to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:18364:72"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The fourth Nullitie on the part of the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T remaineth, now, that wee ſhould in a few words declare the Injuries done to Princes, and forreigne Kings by this Conſpiracie of <hi>Prague.</hi> And firſt of all; it was no ſmall thing ſtrange, that our Triumvirs have ſo ſhamefully exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and rejected from the benefit of the Common Treaty, the Princes and States of <hi>Germany:</hi> whoſe ſtrengths and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories they had already ſwallowed in their moſt greedy hopes. But this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unto all men very abſurd; that the ſame men having neglected, and proſtrated the right of Majeſtie; have remooved out of the Councell of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18364:73"/> like pacification ſo many Kings and Kingdomes, having no dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſacred Empire: whom it princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerned that tranquilitie ſhould bee reſtored to <hi>Europe,</hi> and libertie to <hi>Germany;</hi> and have as it were, with the power of a Dictator denounced a moſt deadly Warre againſt all thoſe, that ſhould oppoſe their Triumvirate.</p>
            <p>For, to ſay nothing of thoſe renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Princes; the King of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> whoſe Siſters Children, after ſo many windie and dilatory promiſes; are ſo cruelly kept out of their poſſeſſions, and Hereditary rights. The King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke;</hi> from whoſe ſon, without hearing or underſtanding his cauſe; the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick of <hi>Bremen,</hi> with the Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane Biſhoprickes were taken away in ſo judiciall a manner. The united and Confederate States of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> againſt whom, under the title of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Germane</hi> libertie; armes joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in conſpiracie with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> are taken up. That is againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18364:73"/> of reaſon, and deſerves not ſo much as any ſhew of excuſe; that the King and Kingdomes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> being engaged in Common armes, and united in a joynt Warre with the Chiefe of the Proteſtants; are ſo diſgracefully proſcribed againſt the law of Nations: and are commanded like ſlaves and vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, to obey the Commands of the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> and if they doe otherwiſe, they are not to be rowted (forſooth) but to be ſwallowed up quite withan armie of 80. Regiments: As if they were not able to obtaine their common peace, as a reward of their owne valour; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the gift of anothers power: or that they ought rather to begge their publike ſafety, as of the good will and pleaſure of their enemies; then by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Armies to wring it from them, being brought upon their knees; or as if they were ignorant, that the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of enemies are falſe hearted; and that peace voluntarily offered is more deceitfull, then reſt purchaſed by ſtrong
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18364:74"/> hand. For, what can be more unjuſt, or more ſenceleſſe; then for forreigne Kingdomes, over which, neither the <hi>Emperor,</hi> nor the <hi>Empire</hi> have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to accept at the pleaſure of the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi> a diſgracefull, diſhonourable, and uncomely Peace; and no leſſe calamitous,<note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Becauſe the <hi> Swedes</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Warre in their owne name, ought to make an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in their owne right. 1626.</note> then ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious to themſelves, and their Allies. Eſpecially, when as the moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had in his owne name denounced. Warre againſt the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> for particular injuries done to himſelfe; and ſet it on foot, the <hi>Saxon</hi> at the firſt labouring againſt it. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, when as in the yeare 1626. that great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> ſet forward with his Armie in <hi>Pruſsia,</hi> againſt the <hi>Polonians:</hi> the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> being never ſo much as provoked, ſent forth the Duke of <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia,</hi> with the Imperiall forces and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, againſt the <hi>Swedes.</hi> And in the yeare 1629.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1629</label> beſieging <hi>Straleſand,</hi> contrary to their faith and promiſe given: they ſhut up the commerce of the <hi>Baltike</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:18364:74"/> Sea: and caſt the Dukes of <hi>Meckle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> out of their Hereditary Eſtates; being proſcribed, and their cauſe never heard. That glorious King being juſtly inſtigated by ſuch notorious Injuries; did endeavour to recover the ſafety of himſelfe and his friends, by Armes; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1630</label> which hee could not obtaine by a friendly Treaty: and tranſporting his Armie into <hi>Germany;</hi> did in his owne name; and under his owne conduct, make warre upon the Emperour: and intimated the cauſes of this revenge, being as neceſſary as lawfull, unto the Colledge of Electors. But having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-runne many places with conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring armes; hee did in his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular name, and in the right of his owne Majeſtie; make divers accords with the Emperour, Electors, and Commanders of his enemies Armies: and ſhortly after joyning the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to him,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> after the Victory of <hi>Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſich:</hi> hee either made, or attempted to make publique Confederacies. Not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18364:75"/> with the Emperour and Leaguers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; but alſo with the Principall States and Circles of the Empire: the <hi>Saxon</hi> not onely conniving thereunto; but alſo granting to that moſt prudent King, full authoritie and power to make peace. Therefore with what Iuſtice can hee at this day exclude the <hi>Swedes,</hi> from having their part in the Common Treatie; who doe ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the ſame Injures: and thoſe that be more grievous ones then they, with a warre no way mittigated; but rather more incenſed? With what conſcience can hee envie the according of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Peace to them, who have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken a Warre upon private and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular cauſes; and at their owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar charge? Why doth hee forbid thoſe to negotiate, for the remedies of their miſchiefes; whom it chiefely concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to have thoſe miſchiefes remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? The quiet, peace and libertie of all are indiviſible, as their warre and injuries were: neither can any better
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18364:75"/> endeavour the reparation of their loſt tranquillitie; then they that labour to purchaſe peace, with the hazard of their owne lives.</p>
            <p>Now if this excluſion of the <hi>Swedes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Becauſe the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> in his owne private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect oweth revenging imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the <hi>Sweds.</hi>
               </note> doe at the firſt ſight appeare to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; it is made much more unjuſt, by the perſon of the <hi>Saxon.</hi> For when the moſt renowned <hi>Guſtavus</hi> did revenge his private Injuries, by a particular War againſt the Emperour; the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> having for another cauſe, ſtirred up the Proteſtants to a rebellion: he, and his being beſieged and loſt, did according to the league made at <hi>Torgaw,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1631</label> entruſt all the fortunes of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to the valour and protection of the <hi>Swedes:</hi> and entred into a ſocietie of Armes and Counſells with them; and ſo being delivered from the preſent danger of the particular cauſe of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> he made the common cauſe of all the Proteſtants; and turned this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate warre into a publique defence. And though now as a perjured man,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18364:76"/> againſt his faith given, and confirmed by his oath and ſignature; hee doth revolt from his Confederates, and labour to purchaſe the amitie of his Enemies, by a Triumvirall conſpiracie. Yet the <hi>Swedes</hi> will not therefore preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that moſt wicked example, and renounce their right; and baſely laying downe their Armes, deſiſt from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging their private Injuries. Which, as before their unhappy Societie entred with him, they had valiantly begunne to doe: ſo after his infamous divorce from them, they will no leſſe happily execute. For having amongſt them ſo many domeſticall examples of vertue, they will not bee imitaters of other Princes in frauds, and perjuries; but in valour and brave actions: as certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowing, that hitherto, perfidious crueltie, cowardiſe, and calamitie, have bene on the Enemies ſide: and on their ſide fidelitie, aſſiſtance of their Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, valour, and therefore alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. And as becommeth brave ſpirits,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18364:76"/> they had rather in a good cauſe die vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, then flye cowardly. Therefore the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> is ſo farre from being able out of his imaginary pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of power, as the Proteſtants Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator; and <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Commiſſarie, to command the <hi>Swedes</hi> to accept of a peace, whether they will or not; or to make an accord with the Emperour in their name: that on the contrary, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Emperour would have granted all their petitions, and righted all their Injuries: yet notwithſtanding, they have reaſon, to ſet on foot, a new and more heavie quarrell againſt the <hi>Saxon.</hi> And to bring againſt him a charge of perfidiouſneſſe, perjurie, breach of covenant, forgetfulneſſe of good turnes; and violation of the law of Nations. Let him therefore firſt in his owne name, make an accord with the <hi>Swedes,</hi> for the Injuries done by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and afterwards by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Commiſſion, he ſhall decide the Controverſies of the Empire. Let the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18364:77"/> perfidious man purge himſelfe; and let him firſt excuſe his owne crimes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee defend other mens.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe the <hi>Swedes</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not baſely forſake their leagues and their troupes.</p>
                  <p>See the Acts and Treaties betwixt the <hi>Sweeds</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi> conceived in the yeare 1635. n. 17. 19. and 28.</p>
               </note>Neither is this of leſſe importance to bee conſidered; that the <hi>Swedes,</hi> after they had once undertaken to defend the Cauſe of the Proteſtants, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Germany;</hi> they made reciprocall leagues with many Princes and States of the Empire, for the defence of the publique Weale. As with them of <hi>Straleſund,</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1628. With the Duke of <hi>Pomerane,</hi> the tenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1630. With the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> the firſt of <hi>September</hi> 1631. With the foure higher Circles, in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Frankford,</hi> in the yeare 1633. And with the States of the <hi>Lower Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony,</hi> in the Convention at <hi>Halberſtadt.</hi> And ſo having called in moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> to the defence of their libertie; they gathered together moſt puiſſant Armies out of many Nations: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by their valour put their enemies to the ſword; at their owne great
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18364:77"/> charge, and greater toyle; they tooke many Cities of <hi>Germany,</hi> and much Munition: and defended them with the ineſtimable loſſe of their King. And therefore they cannot with the ſafety of their honour and reputation, cowardly abandon places valiantly gotten; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they reſtore all things unto their entire condition: nor frivolouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band an Armie no leſſe famous, then noble, without giving them their meanes. For it would bee wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ridiculous, that they ſhould have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſo many moſt ſtrong Forts, with huge expences and dangers: to this end, that they ſhould preſently after reſtore them againe at the pleaſure of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: and that they ſhould have bound ſo many moſt choice, noble, and brave men, with a Military Oath, to the end, that they might caſheere them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when their bodies were maimed, their meanes ſpent, and their wounds yet gaping, miſerable, naked, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed: and as baniſhed men forbidden
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18364:78"/> the uſe of fire and water. This is the propertie of the <hi>Saxon,</hi> and his Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, to value the bodies and ſoules of the ſouldiers at a farthing: to relieve his ſtarved Armies with the oppreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the ſubjects; baſely to abandon things raſhly gotten, to alter or change his friendſhips and hatreds, according to the inconſtancy of Fortune: and in a word, to interpret the Triumvirall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, by the name of a generall peace. The <hi>Swedes</hi> being as noble as famous for their lawrell wreathes, as for their traffique: doe reverence valour as well as Conſtancie; and as they are wiſe in a gowne, ſo are they coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in a ſouldiers coate. When the loſſe or hazard of honour is in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they had rather have a bloudy warre, then a fruitleſſe peace; and doe rather chooſe to redeeme their Confederates by an honourable death, then to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them by diſgracefull flinching, and ſecret turning their backes. As people that have well learned, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18364:78"/> doth any where concerne their friends, doth alſo concerne themſelves, and that a part of the common detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reacheth unto them as particular perſons. Wherefore they will never be induced by any reaſon or force to be ſo unworthy; as by a baſe neglecting of the warre, to delude their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; proſtitute their friends; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to admit of peace upon what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions ſoever, then to treate for it. And rather with readineſſe to embrace the friendſhip of their enemies, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Eſpecially, ſince they doe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly know; that no length of time, no oblivion, ſhall ever wipe away the ſenſe of that danger, whereunto the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> ſaw it ſelfe expoſed by the <hi>Swediſh</hi> forces; and even brought as it were, to the laſt gaſpe. Hee doth not well know the condition of that nation, that doth thinke that any ſuch thing, can fall from them. The nature of <hi>Spaniards</hi> is long to remember of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but quickly to forget good
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18364:79"/> turnes. And howſeover that <hi>Caeſar</hi> of old time would often ſay, that hee could remember all things ſaving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries: the diſpoſition of this preſent <hi>Caeſar</hi> is not ſo; who doth not onely never forgive nor forget the injuries, which hee imagineth to bee offered to himſelfe and his Houſe: but alſo watching for a fit occaſion for a whole age together, doth revenge it upon the innocent Children, and grand-children. It can therefore by no right or reaſon be required of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> that as perſons content with the ſuretiſhip and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the <hi>Saxon,</hi> who hath often ſo perfidiouſly deceiyed them; they ſhould carry away their conquering armies out of the Empire: that they ſhould abandon a publike warre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good ſecuritie of an univerſall peace; and commit all the forces and fortunes of themſelves and their Allies, to the uncertaine will and pleaſure of moſt mercileſſe enemies. As if after their warre ſo valiantly and ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18364:79"/> managed; they were to carry away no other Trophyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the immortall hatred of the <hi>Auſtrians:</hi> no other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, but the everlaſting threats and heart-burnings of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> But I ceaſe further to impaire or blemiſh the moſt renowned acts of that Victorious Nation, with my weake and poore lines. Which, as in time paſt, when the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was deſtroyed; it did reſtore the Weſt part of the World to her libertie: ſo at this day having her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions bent upon the reſtitution of the <hi>Germane</hi> ſafety; The defends her owne cauſe better by armes then by pens; and deſireth not ſo much excuſes for her actions, as praiſes and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:18364:80"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The fifth Nullitie on the part of the French.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Come to the French, a people breathing libertie, by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry derivation of their name. Who, when as by very good right, and with a moſt pious purpoſe, they had engaged themſelves in the common Warre: by the decree of the Triumvirate of <hi>Prague,</hi> againſt all right, and contrary to all pietie; were not onely rejected from the publique pacification; but alſo proſcribed as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Empire; favourers of Heretikes; inſtigators of <hi>Turkes,</hi> and diſturbers of the Chriſtian Common wealth. And under colour of a Warre againſt <hi>Lorraine,</hi> are commanded to be
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18364:80"/> deſtroyed with the whole power of <hi>Germany</hi> joyned together. Indeed,<note place="margin">1. Becauſe the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King by the right of Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Catholike Faith in the Empire. 1631.</note> when as in the yeare 1631. the moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned King of the <hi>Swedes</hi> having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne the Forces of the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> and of the Leaguers; did runne through the Empire without reſiſtance, (the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour being afraid of him; the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> flying; and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> not ſo much as whiſpering againſt him) and took poſſeſſion of the beſt Provinces &amp; Cities of <hi>Germany:</hi> and by that meanes brought the affaires of the Catholikes into grievous ſtraights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent deſtruction. The moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King being ever heretofore a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duer of Heretikes; and a defendor of the Catholikes; fearing leaſt by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of this civill warre, the cauſe of Religion might receive prejudice: did not onely by ſending Embaſſadors to that victorious King, obtaine for all the Catholikes, which were brought under his command; a full libertie and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Religion; but alſo offering
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18364:81"/> to the reſt the remedie of Neutralitie, tooke into his Royall defence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, the Archbiſhopricke of <hi>Triers,</hi> the Biſhoprickes of <hi>Spire</hi> and <hi>Baſill:</hi> and very many other Dukes, Counts, and Cities of <hi>Germany.</hi> And through his moderation no leſſe pious then prudent, he ſtopped the unavoydable ruine of the Catholikes in the Empire; and kept off imminent deſtruction from the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. So the Religion of his Anceſtors being preſerved, and eſtabliſhed; hee ſeeing Princes unjuſtly caſt out by the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> Cities deprived of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; and his neighbours either op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, or ready to bee oppreſſed with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> yoake: joyned his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate armes with the <hi>Swede;</hi> reſtored the Princes to their Territories, and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories to their Princes; Cities to their priviledges; and the Empire to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient rights and dignities: and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all his neighbours and friends from the tyranny of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> And yet notwithſtanding for all theſe his good
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18364:81"/> merits towards Religion and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Common wealth; he is onely not proſcribed by the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> but accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them to be the kindler, fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and advancer of the whole <hi>Germane</hi> Warre: and is alſo with moſt falſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies exclaimed on; as if he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the <hi>Lutherans</hi> for the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Catholike truth. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Emperour himſelfe unto whom the zeale of <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth, cannot bee unknowne, by ſo many warres as have beene made by him againſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks; yet in his Declaration touching the benefits and commodities of the Peace of <hi>Prague,</hi> ſet forth at <hi>Baden</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1635 he doth plainely profeſſe: <hi>That if haply any man ſhall conceive, that in the Treaty of</hi> Prague <hi>ſufficient proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not made for the good of the State, and of Religion; that the cauſe thereof is not to bee imputed to him and his Confederates; but to the moſt Chriſtian King. Who though hee bee commonly ſtiled the eldeſt ſonne of the Church; yet hee was not onely
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18364:82"/> not aſhamed in the beginning of this Warre, to ſue for the aſsiſtance of Heretikes; to call in the King of</hi> Sweden <hi>a ſtranger to aide him; to make a ſolemne League with him; to feede and re-enforce both their ſtrengths being joyned together; and of his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per motion, without any cauſe, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to his promiſe given, to invade the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the Empire: but doth ſtill daily endeavour to ſtirre up the Princes and States againſt him, being pulled away from the Emperour. Yea more, after that by the Victory of</hi> Nordingen, <hi>very many were added to his party; hee with armes in his hand, tooke poſſeſsion of the Cities which were brought under his Command: caſt the garriſons of the Catholikes out of them; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored thoſe of the Heretikes; and as much as in him lyeth, doth endevour to ſtoppe the progreſſe of peace and Catholike Religion in the Empire. Inſomuch, that he tooke the boldneſſe to promiſe the Duke of Saxony, if hee would range himſelfe on his ſide; hee would not onely procure him the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace; but that hee would labour
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18364:82"/> with tooth and naile, that the Hereſie of the Lutherans, with the reſt of the Sects might bee publikely eſtabliſhed in the Kingdome of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>and the Provinces united to it.</hi> Good God, what a thing is this? the moſt Chriſtian King, who, when the reſt turned their backes, did by his interceſſion alone made to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> preſerve the Catholike faith in moſt of the Provinces of <hi>Germany:</hi> did hee with the utmoſt of his ſtrength ſtop the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe and increaſe thereof! Hee that delivered divers Biſhops out of the fires of their enemies; did hee adde flame to the Warre againſt the Catholikes! He that ſtripped the Heretikes of <hi>France</hi> out of all their ſtrength, and laid them on their backes was it his care, to raiſe up the Sectaries of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient power! Theſe are frivolous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of his adverſaries; who, when they cannot cloake their invaſions by a title of civill right, they betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the counterfeit vizard of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Religion: and as if the warre
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18364:83"/> were made in <hi>Germany</hi> for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Religion, not of Tyranny: they traduce all thoſe that ſtand for the libertie of the Empire, as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes; or at the leaſt, favourers of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Becauſe the Protection of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and States of the Empire, cannot bee charged to be the French Kings fault.</note>The true and principall cauſe of this quarrell and indignation is, that the moſt Chriſtian King when things were, in regard of any other helpe, in a deſperate condition; hee received the Archbiſhop of <hi>Triers,</hi> being oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> into his patronage and protection: but when hee had caſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of the Citie and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorie of <hi>Triers,</hi> he reſtored the Prince freely to his rights and dignitie.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1632</label> That then having joyned his armes with the <hi>Swedes:</hi> he delivered divers other States of the Empire; as namely, the <hi>Palatines,</hi> the <hi>Alſatians,</hi> and the <hi>Weſtraſians,</hi> from the pillings and pollings of the <hi>Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the <hi>Lorraines.</hi> That hee did by no new nor unheard of example; but ſuch a one as was laid downe before
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18364:83"/> him, and delivered to him from his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; ſet limits to the ambition of his enemies, and ſtoutly defended the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> libertie. The protection of people in diſtreſſe; the rayſing up of the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; and the reſtoring of them that are caſt out; is naturall to Kings: and doth not belong unto them ſo much by the right of their Scepter, as by the law of humanitie. It is the duty of a good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to governe his ſubjects, and to protect his Allies: neither is there any greater inſtrument or teſtimony of good governement; then when neighbours are preſerved from the hands of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. And if by common right it be a fit thing for all Kings to ſuccour thoſe that be afflicted; yet none did ever more juſtly, and happily practiſe it; then the moſt glorious Monarches of the <hi>French:</hi> who, for this laſt age and more (to lay aſide thoſe things which are more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and more forreigne) have ſent fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent aides unto the Catholike and Proteſtant States of the Empire, againſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18364:84"/> the Invaſions of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1534</label> So <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis I.</hi> in the yeare 1534. joyning his armes with <hi>Philip</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Haſsia,</hi> reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Vlricus</hi> Duke of <hi>Wittembergh</hi> after 15. yeares baniſhment, being caſt out by thoſe of <hi>Swawben,</hi> through the faithleſſe dealings of the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> to all the rights and Territories which <hi>Ferdinand I.</hi> had formerly poſſeſſed under the name of an Imperiall Fee. So <hi>Henry II.</hi> making a League with the Proteſtants, in the yeare 1552.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1552</label> brought home <hi>Iohn Frederike</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the Landgrave of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> being like ſlaves ſhut up in priſon by <hi>Charles V.</hi> for above 5. yeares together; contrary to his faith and promiſe, and reſtored them to their former libertie. So in the yeare 1620.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1620</label> when by the Vnion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and troubles of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Catholikes were brought into great ſtreights; and the Emperour himſelfe being then in a manner beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in <hi>Vienna,</hi> ranne a hazard not onely to loſe the Kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18364:84"/> 
               <hi>Hungary,</hi> but even his owne Hereditary Provinces: <hi>Lewis XIII.</hi> being as well moved with the zeale of preſerving the Catholike Religion; as with the often iterated intreaties of the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Embaſſadours to the Aſſembly at <hi>Vlme,</hi> diſperſed the forces and Councels of all the united Princes, procured a truce betwixt both Armies; perſwaded the Prince of the <hi>Tranſilvanians</hi> to peace, and ſo giving the Emperour liberty to breath; delivered the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> from moſt certaine ruine. Now if the Emperour abuſing ſo many favours done him, doe turne his victories obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the Heretikes and Rebels, into a ſlaughter of innocents, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his neighbours; and doe tranſ-ferre the fortunes of the Empire to the private benefit of his owne Family: no man ought to thinke it ſtrange, if the moſt Chriſtian King hauing beene the authour of all thoſe Victories, doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to moderate his enormous uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations; and to reduce them to the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18364:85"/> of the ancient right: eſpecially, ſince he well knowes, what difference there is betwixt the Common-wealth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and will not ſo advance the rights of the Empire, or of the Allies thereof; that he will depreſſe or hinder the cauſe,<note place="margin">3. The moſt illuſtrious Elector of <hi>Trevers</hi> (or <hi>Trier</hi>) did juſtly and ſeaſonably obtaine the protection of the French. M. M. <hi>Author</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pro Domo Auſtriaca. Bruxellis editi.</hi> 1635. <hi>Richard. Waſſerburgh. in Antiquit. Galliae Belgicae lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 102. 943.</note> or exerciſe of the Catholike Religion. And whereas that Bundler of calumnies, that Pamphleter of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> doth traduce this protection of the neighbour Princes; and make it as an invaſion of forreigne Provinces: that is eaſily refuted, by the vanitie of the lye it ſelfe. For as it appeareth by the ancient and Authenticall Stories, the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke of <hi>Triers,</hi> with the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſuffragane Biſhoprickes of <hi>Metz, Toul</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> being very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently united to the Kingdome of the <hi>French;</hi> were at length, in the yeare 943. by the misfortune and imprudencie of <hi>Lewis VI.</hi> called the <hi>Tranſmarine,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred unto the Emperour <hi>Otho II.</hi> Yet they ever after flouriſhed and continued under the amitie and patronage of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18364:85"/> 
               <hi>French,</hi> though Cities ſubject to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: and the Prelates of thoſe Cities, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and obtained the aide and protection of the <hi>French;</hi> without any prejudice to the Empire, or detriment to their owne libertie. As amongſt others, in the yeare 1337. <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Aſpremont,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1337</label> Biſhop of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dun,</hi> ſued to King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Valois.</hi> In the yeare 1450. <hi>Conrade Bayer,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1450</label> Biſhop of <hi>Metz,</hi> ſued to <hi>Rene</hi> of <hi>Anjou</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorraine:</hi> and in the yeare 1467.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1467</label> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Liege</hi> to <hi>Lewis II.</hi> the French King; and to <hi>Charles</hi> the Bold, Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> All theſe deſired and obtained of theſe Princes, ſupport and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection againſt the Rebels, or invaders of their Eccleſiaſticall rights: without any prejudice to the Majeſtie of the Empire. And whereas that mercenary ſcribler a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth; that by a moſt ancient League made betweene the Biſhops of <hi>Triers,</hi> and the Counts and Dukes of <hi>Lutzemburgh;</hi> the Archbiſhoprick and Cities of <hi>Triers,</hi> is and hath beene under the protection and Advocacie of the Dukes of <hi>Lutzem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh;</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:18364:86"/> and that therefore the moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Elector of <hi>Triers,</hi> ought rather to have ſued for the protection of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who at this day is in poſſeſſion of the Dutchy of <hi>Lutzemburgh,</hi> then the forreigne patronage of the <hi>French;</hi> is a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and a fooliſh allegation.</p>
            <p>For we know, that ſome few ages ſince, the Counts of <hi>Lutzemburgh</hi> did volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily offer their protection to them of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guilielmus Kyriander in Annalibus Trevirorum. p. <hi>158.</hi> &amp; <hi>194. 1374.</hi>
               </note> and that the Emperour <hi>Charles IV.</hi> who was of that Houſe; to the end that he might purchaſe the Empire for his moſt ſtupid ſonne <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> in the yeare 1374. did not onely pay unto <hi>Cuno</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Trires,</hi> a huge ſumme of money for his Electorall voice; but alſo promiſed him a mercenary protection againſt all enemies of what condition ſoever. And that ſoone after,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1376</label> in the yeare 1376. a controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Biſhop and the Citie touching matter of jurisdiction being put over to him; he did order that Citie &amp; State to be wholly and fully ſubject to the Prelate: which notwithſtanding is yet at this day
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18364:86"/> called in queſtion by the Citizens. But we know alſo, that this protection did not deprive the Archbiſhop of his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute right; nor that it did of one under the protection of the Houſe of <hi>Lutzemburgh,</hi> make him a ſlave unto the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> &amp; that a Free Prince when the Patronage of his former Protector faileth him, may juſtly obtaine the Protection of a new Patron: eſpecially when ſuch a neceſſitie hangs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his head, that he cannot bee preſerved, but by a moſt preſent remedy. Which, ſince the moſt illuſtrious Elector of <hi>Triers</hi> did; when he was in danger to bee utterly deſtroyed by the <hi>Swedes</hi> being hard at his backe; there is no reaſon, why the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould bee offended at it: who at that time were ſo farre from being able to give aide to others, by right of prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; that on the contrary they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a moſt perilous Warre with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> did loſe whole Provinces and Cities of their greateſt ſtrength: as <hi>Venlo, Ruremond, Maſtricht</hi> and <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:18364:87"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Becauſe the Emperour endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to make the quarrells of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note>Neither is the cunning of the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> here to be paſſed over; who whilſt in the peace of <hi>Prague,</hi> they make a ſhew to take care of the tranquilitie of <hi>Germany;</hi> yet neglecting all the reſpects of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; they onely provide for the perticuler benefit of their owne. For whereas there have been of old time, many controverſies and ſome Warres betwixt the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> touching the Kingdoms of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Sicilye,</hi> and <hi>Navar;</hi> and touching the Duchies of <hi>Milan</hi> and <hi>Burgundy.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> juſtly laying claime to thoſe things from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> which had beene un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly taken from them: The Emperour denouncing publique Warre againſt the <hi>French,</hi> makes the quarells which were particular to him and his; common to the whole Empire: ties and engages all the Princes to his owne domeſticall intereſt; and the better to maintaine the Tyranny of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> entangles all the <hi>Germans</hi> in a forreigne Warre. A ſubtiltie long ago attempted by the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> but ever ſtrongly rejected by the States of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18364:87"/> For ſo in the yeare 1492.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1492</label>
               <note place="margin">Extant apud Goldaſtum Conſtitut. Imper. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>4. 1526. 1542.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian I.</hi> in the Diet at <hi>Coblentz;</hi> and <hi>Charles V.</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Electors, dated at <hi>Madrid</hi> the 29. of <hi>November</hi> 1526. and againe, in the yeare 1542. in the Diet at <hi>Spire:</hi> did traduce <hi>Charles VIII.</hi> and <hi>Francis. I.</hi> the French Kings, as diſturbers of the Chriſtian Common Wealth; inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of other mens Principalities; and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of the <hi>Turkes</hi> and Heretikes; and did in vaine deſire, that the Warres made againſt them out of private reſpects, might be revenged by the power of whole <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> as injuries offered to the Empire.</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner, their ſucceſſours have omitted no meanes of endeavour; that they might by ſome publique device of the Diet, proſcribe the Confederate States of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> as Rebells to the <hi>Empire,</hi> and gilty of high Treaſon, for ſhaking off the yoke of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> Which, nevertheleſſe the States of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> in the Diet at <hi>Wormbs,</hi> in the yeare 1578. and in the late Diet at <hi>Ratisbone</hi> 1630.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1578</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1630</label> abſolutely refuſed to doe.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:18364:88"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Becauſe the cauſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not at all to the Emperour.</note>And the cauſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> is moſt vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aleaged to bee a motive for this Warre: Becauſe that <hi>Auſtraſia</hi> many ages ago uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Scepter of the <hi>French,</hi> and a principall Patrimony of the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> under both the races of their Kings;<note place="margin">980.</note> at length, in the yeare 980. it was taken away from the <hi>French</hi> by the King of the <hi>Germanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aimoinus Hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>44.</hi> p. <hi>510.</hi> editionis Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herianae. Continuator Chronici Flodoardi, qui extat To. <hi>2.</hi> Hiſt. Gall. editorum a V. C. Andrea Ducheſnio. <hi>1636.</hi> p. <hi>626.</hi> Extant ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. p. <hi>797.</hi>
               </note> under a pretence of a right of homage to bee done to them for it: and ſo it was by <hi>Lothaire</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King conferred upon the <hi>Emperour Otho</hi> the Second, as a Fee; againſt the will and liking of the Princes and Peeres of that Kingdome. Vnto which things, <hi>Gerbert,</hi> afterwards Archbiſhop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> and at the laſt Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath reference in his 35. <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>That</hi> Adal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bero <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Rheims, <hi>tooke hoſtages of the Nobles of the Kingdome of</hi> Lorraine, <hi>and compelled them to doe homage unto the Emperours ſonne, but under the protection and Signorie of the French King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if in the ſucceeding times the Dukes of <hi>Lorraine</hi> being ſituate in the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18364:88"/> confines of both theſe great Princes, and through the changeable condition of their fortune wavering betwixt both, have beene faithfull to neither, but have withdrawne their homage from both. Certainely it doth no more belong to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> to mingle the intereſt of the <hi>Empire</hi> with the cauſe of <hi>Lorraine;</hi> then it was fit for the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> with Clandiſtine mariage and open armes, to diſturbe be peace of <hi>France,</hi> and with moſt injurious calumnies to ſcandalize the Majeſtie of the <hi>French</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>But I ceaſe to preſſe and obtrude a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to a moſt juſt cauſe;<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> which having beene often approoved from heaven, hath left more ignominie then glory to the enemies of it. And from thoſe things that have beene hitherto declared; I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the onely ſcope of the Tranſ-action of <hi>Prague,</hi> was to advance the greatneſſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> whether by right or wrong; to make the <hi>Empire</hi> together with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18364:89"/> of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to him: and in a word, by bringing under the reſt of the Kingdomes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to eſtabliſh every where the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Monarchie. And ſo almoſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very article of this conſpiracie; whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever are either adverſe to the Spaniards, or ſuſpected to bee ſo; (as the <hi>French, Swedes,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi>) are excluded out of the Peace, and aſſaulted with the common armes: and whoſoever are friends, neighbours, or Allies unto them, are moſt bountifully rewarded out of the ſpoiles of the proſcribed. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed, to the end, that the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> might abſolutely rule over <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> the Eelector <hi>Palatine</hi> (the principall Pillar of the Empire) ſhould firſt have beene proſcribed: whoſe forces, alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and affection to his Countrey, have beene long ſince adverſe to <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Counſells. Then when the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> was ſtricken downe, his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Diginities muſt bee beſtowed upon the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards:</hi> not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18364:89"/> only becauſe the Countries of the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> doe lie as a bulwarke unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Patrimonie, to defend it againſt the Heretike Princes of upper <hi>Germany;</hi> but alſo becauſe by this meanes the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians</hi> will alwaies have voices enow in a readineſſe in the Colledge of Electors. To conclude, to the end that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour might make uſe of all the ſtrength of <hi>Germany</hi> at his pleaſure; an Armie of eighty Regiments to be levied and paied by the Princes themſelves; is committed to the abſolute command of the King of <hi>Hungary:</hi> by which, not onely the Dukes and States that bee refractory, may be chaſtiſed; but alſo that power, which is left to the Proteſtants may bee cut up by the rootes. So <hi>Germany</hi> being ſubdued and brought under, and <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine</hi> recovered; it ſeemed afterwards an eaſie matter to invade <hi>France,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer <hi>Holland;</hi> and to bring <hi>Britaine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoake, as being their due long ſince by a mariage with <hi>Spaine;</hi> as the Emperour confeſſeth in his Declaration
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18364:90"/> of the cauſes and benefits of the Peace of <hi>Prague,</hi> ſet forth at <hi>Baden</hi> the eighth of <hi>Iune</hi> 1635. <hi>That Peace being on this manner ſettled, his Nephew the King of</hi> Spaine <hi>will very eaſily reduce the</hi> Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>to obedience.</hi> Therefore it is ſo farre off, that by this Tranſ-action Peace and publike tranquillity hath beene ſought; that on the contrary the light of peace being every where put out, warre hath beene kindled throughout all <hi>Europe;</hi> and all the Princes whether they would or not, have beene entangled in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall armes of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable is the Peace, which is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by open force! a moſt dolefull Tranquillitie, which troubles al things! a moſt treacherous ſecuritie, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one hath cauſe to diſtruſt! Certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, feare and terrour are weake bonds of love; which when they are removed, thoſe that ceaſe to feare, will beginne to hate. It is certaine, that a faithfull Peace can be onely there, where men are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reconciled; and that it cannot bee
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18364:90"/> hoped to be of any long continuance in that place where ſervitude is aimed at. Certainely, no mortall man will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue longer than needs muſt in ſuch a condition, as is irkeſome to him; and evermore in an uncertaine quiet: though concord doe in ſhew continue, yet the opening and remembring of offences paſt; will ſtill be feared. That is a true tranquillitie, which all men approve, and every one deſires; by which anger is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into friendſhip; hatred growes into leagues of amitie; and an equalitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerved among all, and the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mneſtia</hi> extended to all, the enemies either by greatneſſe of good turnes, or forgetting of injuries are turned to friends.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
